<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Posts on Nitin Savant</title>
		<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/</link>
		<description>Recent content in Posts on Nitin Savant</description>
		<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
		<lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="nitinsavant.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
		<item>
			<title>What is this Snapchat thing?</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/snapchat/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/snapchat/</guid>
			<description>While in Istanbul, I met a bright Turkish teenager while eating at the dorm cafeteria. We chatted for a bit and as I got up to leave, I asked if he had Facebook. He said, &amp;ldquo;no, but I have Snapchat.&amp;rdquo;
I first tried Snapchat in late 2012, about a year after it&amp;rsquo;s launch. The app let you to take and share photos with your friends. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t really get it.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While in Istanbul, I met a bright Turkish teenager while eating at the dorm cafeteria. We chatted for a bit and as I got up to leave, I asked if he had Facebook. He said, &ldquo;no, but I have Snapchat.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I first tried Snapchat in late 2012, about a year after it&rsquo;s launch. The app let you to take and share photos with your friends. But I didn&rsquo;t really get it. Couldn&rsquo;t I already do this with Facebook, Instagram, or a text? Apparently, the difference with Snapchat was that the photo would disappear 10 seconds after it was viewed. But why I would want my photos to disappear? And if I did, couldn&rsquo;t the person just take a screenshot? It felt weird. And none of my friends used it. A social app is pretty useless without your friends. I quickly gave up and uninstalled the app.</p>
<p>A year later, I gave it another shot. By this time, a few friends were using the app and sending me &ldquo;snaps&rdquo; — photos or videos in Snapchat lingo. This time I just couldn&rsquo;t figure out how to use the app. Snapchat was one of the first apps where you swiped both vertically and horizontally to navigate its screens. I was only familiar with vertical scrolling — the way all websites and most apps worked at that time — and this new mix overwhelmed my brain. I gave up and uninstalled the app once again.</p>
<p>Over the last few months, while traveling alongside some heavy Snapchat users, I gave the app one more shot. I think I finally get it. Since it took me a while, I wanted to figure out what I had missed. You know besides getting old and becoming more resistant to change. Here&rsquo;s what I came up with:</p>
<p><strong>It&rsquo;s an experience.</strong> Let&rsquo;s start with Snapchat&rsquo;s distinguishing feature: photos and videos that disappear. While it&rsquo;s easy to conclude that the app exists to allow teenagers to send inappropriate photos to each other, what Snapchat has actually achieved is more impressive. We often choose to collect things (e.g. buying records, cars, houses, etc.), but sometimes we choose to pursue experiences (e.g. attending concerts, traveling to new cities, trying new foods, etc.). In a small way, Snapchat is social media for choosing experiences over things. When you have just one chance to see something before it&rsquo;s gone forever, you&rsquo;ll pay more attention than when you&rsquo;re mindlessly scrolling through your neverending Facebook feed.</p>
<p><strong>It encourages creation.</strong> We spend a lot of our time consuming things (e.g. watching Netflix, reading books, etc.), but sometimes when we&rsquo;re feeling inspired, we create things (e.g. writing a letter, taking a picture, cooking a meal, etc.). Unlike most popular apps, Snapchat encourages you to create. When you open Facebook, Instagram, or Twitter, you first see your feed — that endless stream of pictures, posts, likes, and comments. To actually share something of your own, you click a separate button. When you open Snapchat, however, you&rsquo;re taken to the camera and nudged to take a picture and share it. We aren&rsquo;t writing novels or creating works of art but it&rsquo;s a start.</p>
<p><strong>It&rsquo;s not forever.</strong> Snapchat realized that we don&rsquo;t necessarily want everything we share to be stored forever. We&rsquo;ve all spent some time — hours in my case — cleaning up our social media feeds by deleting old photos and posts. With Snapchat, there&rsquo;s no need. Everything is stored only in your own memory, similar to a conversation you might have at the local cafe or a phone call with your best friend. There doesn&rsquo;t seem to be a need to store most of what we do in our day-to-day lives.</p>
<p><strong>It&rsquo;s more personal.</strong> For me, 1-to-1 messaging (e.g. email, text, etc.) remains the most powerful way to connect. When a friend sends a photo, video, or article, with a  personalized message, I always check it out. When that same friend uses social media to share with everyone, I rarely even see it. More than other social media, Snapchat makes sharing feel personal. After taking a photo, you&rsquo;re asked to select individual friends to share with. It&rsquo;s a conversation rather than an announcement. While Snapchat has introduced a way to share a snap with all your friends (called Stories), these snaps are placed in a separate inbox and they retain the Snapchat feel; Stories last only 24 hours and there are no likes or comments to watch and obsess over.</p>
<p><strong>It&rsquo;s not everything.</strong> Snapchat isn&rsquo;t the be-all and end-all of social media. Facebook, as my defacto address book, is probably my most important app. Instagram and iCloud Photo Sharing help me keep up with friends and family.  And Twitter keeps me connected to the larger world around. Snapchat has showed me something though; there&rsquo;s plenty yet to come out of the fun and crazy world of social media. I just hope I can keep up.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Over It</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/get-over-it/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/get-over-it/</guid>
			<description>I did it. After 3 years of using my iPhone 5 — one of the sleek 4-inch phones they don&amp;rsquo;t make anymore — without a case, it finally happened. I cracked my screen. As I removed my gym towel from my backpack today, my iPhone fluttered out behind it and smacked onto my room&amp;rsquo;s tile floor.
It sucked. Not because I needed a new phone. It still works. Not because I had to squint through a spider web to use it.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I did it. After 3 years of using my iPhone 5 — one of the sleek 4-inch phones they don&rsquo;t make anymore — without a case, it finally happened. I cracked my screen. As I removed my gym towel from my backpack today, my iPhone fluttered out behind it and smacked onto my room&rsquo;s tile floor.</p>
<p>It sucked. Not because I needed a new phone. It still works. Not because I had to squint through a spider web to use it. It&rsquo;s not cracked that bad. It sucked because I&rsquo;m no longer the guy that successfully carries around his iPhone without a case. I liked being that guy. It felt good that I was careful (or lucky) enough to be that guy. But now, I&rsquo;m just a guy that cracked his iPhone. How original.</p>
<p>My frustration lingered. I took turns being angry at my backpack, the tile floor, and myself. I take pride in rarely complaining, but I tried something different this time. Over the next few hours, I recited my ordeal to anyone who would listen. And you know what? It helped. I got over it. Let&rsquo;s move on.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>If You&#39;re Not Going To Listen...</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/advice/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/advice/</guid>
			<description>After just a few hours walking through Istanbul, I feel a distinctly different vibe from the rest of Europe. Istanbul is what&amp;rsquo;s known as a transcontinental city — a city that spreads across multiple continents, Europe and Asia in this case. And it shows. The food is spicier, the clothing is more traditional, and there isn&amp;rsquo;t much English to be heard. Before catching my flight from Croatia to Istanbul, I made use of my last opportunity to eavesdrop and heard this tidbit from the dinner table next to me.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After just a few hours walking through Istanbul, I feel a distinctly different vibe from the rest of Europe. Istanbul is what&rsquo;s known as a transcontinental city — a city that spreads across multiple continents, Europe and Asia in this case.  And it shows. The food is spicier, the clothing is more traditional, and there isn&rsquo;t much English to be heard.  Before catching my flight from Croatia to Istanbul, I made use of my last opportunity to eavesdrop and heard this tidbit from the dinner table next to me.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Well, if you&rsquo;re not going to listen to my advice, why&rsquo;d you ask for my help?&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;ve heard this complaint many times.  I&rsquo;ve heard it from my friends. I&rsquo;ve heard it from my family. I&rsquo;ve even heard it from myself. I most recently heard it on a podcast where two &ldquo;life coaches&rdquo; were discussing frustrations with certain clients.</p>
<p>Everyone has been there. A friend comes to you asking for guidance; they&rsquo;re in need of help to work through some problem they have. After listening to their problem, you consult your own life experience and instruct them on how to fix their problem. You provide a well-thought and logical solution, and you&rsquo;re confident it&rsquo;ll work. BUT, instead of graciously thanking you and running off to take action, your friend says &ldquo;Ehh, that&rsquo;s not gonna work for me&rdquo;, &ldquo;Ehh, I already tried that&rdquo;, or &ldquo;Ehh, I don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s right.&rdquo; Or they listen to your advice, go back, and don&rsquo;t end up doing anything about it.</p>
<p>One common reaction is for you, the advice-giver, to get upset and think &ldquo;Well, if you&rsquo;re not going to listen to my advice, why&rsquo;d you ask for my help?&rdquo; But isn&rsquo;t that kind of a selfish way of looking at it? You&rsquo;re essentially saying, &ldquo;This is MY advice, and I&rsquo;M going to help you.&rdquo; When your friend — you know, the one who actually needed the support — doesn&rsquo;t support your advice, you feel rejected and hurt. And this is completely valid.</p>
<p>Stepping back for a moment, I think there&rsquo;s a collective misunderstanding of the situation. The problem isn&rsquo;t that your friend needs advice.  They already know, inside themselves, what they need to do. The problem is their fears and their insecurities, that inner resistance that prevents them from doing what they know they should do. The only real solution is for your friend to recognize this and muster the courage to act in spite of it.</p>
<p>So then what are you, the person formerly known as the advice-giver, to do? All you need to do is create a safe space and provide them the opportunity to talk through their fears and work through their insecurities. No judgement. No advice. Just be there. That&rsquo;s all they need. Through that, maybe their situation will improve&hellip;maybe it won&rsquo;t. But as much as you want to &ldquo;fix&rdquo; their problem, as much as that would give you YOUR satisfaction, there really is nothing here for you to fix.</p>
<p>This sounds simple, but it&rsquo;s certainly not easy. Most times, the solution is staring your friend right in the face, and they just can&rsquo;t see it. When this happens, try to remember, it&rsquo;s never really about the nail.</p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Simple Pleasures</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/simple-pleasures/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/simple-pleasures/</guid>
			<description>I know. It&amp;rsquo;s been a month since I wrote, and that last one doesn&amp;rsquo;t even count. Since then, I spent 10 exhausting yet amazing days home in Los Angeles and then another week battling jet lag while getting settled in Croatia. We&amp;rsquo;re staying in Cavtat, a small coastal town at Croatia&amp;rsquo;s southern tip. The city is full of tourists, and you can&amp;rsquo;t really blame &amp;lsquo;em. With dozens of seafood restaurants, strikingly clear blue water, and daily sunsets that flood the sky with color; Cavtat is the perfect place to spend a summer vacation.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I know. It&rsquo;s been a month since I wrote, and that last one doesn&rsquo;t even count. Since then, I spent 10 exhausting yet amazing days home in Los Angeles and then another week battling jet lag while getting settled in Croatia. We&rsquo;re staying in Cavtat, a small coastal town at Croatia&rsquo;s southern tip. The city is full of tourists, and you can&rsquo;t really blame &lsquo;em. With dozens of seafood restaurants, strikingly clear blue water, and daily sunsets that flood the sky with color; Cavtat is the perfect place to spend a summer vacation. And you can only really come in the summer. The city quite literally shuts down from November to March when the usually warm sun goes into hibernation.</p>
<p>On a quiet night last week, my stomach growls at me as I walk along the Adriatic Sea looking for a place to eat. I sit down just after sunset, a bit impatient having been rejected — there were no open tables — by my restaurant of choice. Tired from a long day exploring the walled city of Dubrovnik under 95°F heat, I grab the menu already on my table and have a look.</p>
<p>A minute later, a waitress greets me with a smile and asks if I&rsquo;d like something to drink. Since the menu only lists beer, I ask about the wine.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Red or white?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Red.&rdquo; She begins to describe the qualities of a local red wine, but I&rsquo;m not really listening.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How much for a glass?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;24 kuna.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I&rsquo;ll take one.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Having already looked at TripAdvisor reviews, I order the touted beef risotto. She gives me a big smile and says &ldquo;Great choice!&rdquo;. Throughout this usually boring interaction, she carries herself with a quiet exuberance that is infectious.</p>
<p>I begin to sip my wine — which tastes like a California Cab — enjoying the fact that it&rsquo;s actually warm. I&rsquo;m not sure why, but most restaurants over the last few months have served chilled red wine. I&rsquo;m not a fan.</p>
<p>Amidst the patio chatter, a familiar song plays. I couldn&rsquo;t tell you its name, but it&rsquo;s unmistakably the powerful voice of Rob Thomas. As a good friend of mine will tell you, &ldquo;Rob&rsquo;s voice in-concert sounds exactly like it does on records!&rdquo; Apparently, I state this emphatically whenever someone plays his songs.</p>
<p>As I savor my risotto, I notice a girl, maybe 5 years old, looking over at me from the table in front. I offer her a quick smile.</p>
<p>Without flinching, she smiles right back with THE warmest smile. I obviously can&rsquo;t contain returning an even bigger smile.</p>
<p>This has never happened. Most often when I respond to a kid&rsquo;s gaze with a smile, they quickly look away. Somehow, I had passed my waitress&rsquo; joy to this beautiful little girl. And she had given it right back to me.</p>
<p>After we exchange a couple more fun glances, her family pays their bill and gets up to leave. As the girl walks by me, I smile one last time, and she sends it right back with a smile that just melts my heart.</p>
<p>This little girl and I never spoke one word to each other — and we&rsquo;ll certainly never cross paths again — but I&rsquo;ll never forget her smile and how it made me feel.</p>
<p>As I process what&rsquo;s happened, I narrate a potential blog post in my head. This isn&rsquo;t uncommon for me but often happens while I&rsquo;m in the shower or somewhere else that I can&rsquo;t easily write. And by the time I do find a computer, the spark is gone. Deciding not to let that happen, I reach into my backpack, grab my journal, and over the next 15 minutes, write basically this entire post.</p>
<p>Ready to leave, I flag down my waitress to request the bill. I&rsquo;ve learned that in Europe, unless you ask for the bill, they just won&rsquo;t bring it. As my waitress hands me the bill, I first ask for her name and then practice being vulnerable by telling her how great of a waitress she&rsquo;s been. She thanks me graciously and reaches out her hand to shake mine.</p>
<p>As I sip the last of my rather large glass of wine — or what my friends would call a &ldquo;Nitin pour&rdquo; — I realize how thankful I feel, not only because of this evening&rsquo;s simple pleasures, but also because of my ability to share them with you.</p>
<p>If you ever find yourself in Cavtat, do yourself a favor and grab a seat at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Pizzeria-Desetka-Cavtat/148248941979510">Pizzeria Desetka.</a></p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Movies</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/movies/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/movies/</guid>
			<description>On a random night a few months ago, I asked my roommate how many movies he thought he&amp;rsquo;d watched in his life. Fast forward four hours, it&amp;rsquo;s 2AM, my roommate is fast asleep, and I finish the list. I like making lists; there&amp;rsquo;s something about making a list that&amp;rsquo;s fun. Before you click below, take a guess at how many movies you&amp;rsquo;ve watched in your life.
Movies</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On a random night a few months ago, I asked my roommate how many movies he thought he&rsquo;d watched in his life. Fast forward four hours, it&rsquo;s 2AM, my roommate is fast asleep, and I finish the list. I like making lists; there&rsquo;s something about making a list that&rsquo;s fun. Before you click below, take a guess at how many movies you&rsquo;ve watched in your life.</p>
<p><a href="https://nitinsavant.herokuapp.com/lists/movies">Movies</a></p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Why I&#39;m Traveling</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/why-im-traveling/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/why-im-traveling/</guid>
			<description>One country down, eleven to go. I almost wrote about how the month flew by, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure that was true. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;ll dig deeper. Until now I haven&amp;rsquo;t said much about why I&amp;rsquo;m traveling.
Over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve read a lot of self-help material. Too much. I figured there was a universal formula for happiness, and I set out to find it. I stopped using social media and watching television.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One country down, eleven to go. I almost wrote about how the month flew by, but I wasn&rsquo;t sure that was true. Instead, I&rsquo;ll dig deeper. Until now I haven&rsquo;t said much about why I&rsquo;m traveling.</p>
<p>Over the years, I&rsquo;ve read a lot of self-help material. Too much. I figured there was a universal formula for happiness, and I set out to find it. I stopped using social media and watching television. I became an early riser. I tried yoga and meditation. I started journaling. I reduced my possessions. I began cooking and eating healthier. I reduced my drinking. I never did try what seemed to be the most universal life tip. Travel.</p>
<p>Then three years ago, I hopped aboard a last minute trip to Costa Rica with a great friend. And I loved it. I loved being outside. I loved experiencing the culture and trying new things. I loved meeting and being around adventurous people. I came home with a different perspective and knew that I needed more of that.</p>
<p>In the three years since, I did a lot of other things that weren&rsquo;t traveling. I worked hard at a job that wasn&rsquo;t a good fit for me. I worked hard to salvage a relationship that wasn&rsquo;t meant to be. Last year I came across an embarrassingly simple piece of advice that shook me with its rawness.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;If you&rsquo;re unhappy, change something.&rdquo; ~Sue Grafton</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So I began making changes. Leaving my friends, family, and hometown to travel was a big one.</p>
<p>A change by itself won&rsquo;t give you much. The experience that comes out of it though can teach you something. When I began eating healthier, I noticed something weird. After a meal, I actually felt good. I&rsquo;d heard people talk about feeling &ldquo;sluggish&rdquo; and &ldquo;bloated&rdquo; after they ate, but I didn&rsquo;t really understand what they meant. David Foster Wallace sums it up nicely.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;There are these two young fish swimming along and they happen to meet an older fish swimming the other way, who nods at them and says &ldquo;Morning, boys. How&rsquo;s the water?&rdquo; And the two young fish swim on for a bit, and then eventually one of them looks over at the other and goes &ldquo;What the hell is water?&rdquo; ~David Foster Wallace</p>
</blockquote>
<p>By traveling, I hope to discover the water in my life. And while I no longer think there is some universal formula for life, I plan to find something that works for me.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Cafe in the Dark</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/cafe-in-the-dark/</link>
			<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/cafe-in-the-dark/</guid>
			<description>A group of us recently visited what&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;Cafe in the Dark.&amp;rdquo; It is what it sounds like, a place to hang and drink coffee in the dark. But it&amp;rsquo;s not just dark, it&amp;rsquo;s pitch-black. Upon arriving, a blind host led three friends and I inside to our table. We shuffled along in a single file line, placing our right hand on the right shoulder of the person in front, and praying that we didn&amp;rsquo;t fall flat on our faces.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A group of us recently visited what&rsquo;s called &ldquo;Cafe in the Dark.&rdquo; It is what it sounds like, a place to hang and drink coffee in the dark. But it&rsquo;s not just dark, it&rsquo;s pitch-black. Upon arriving, a blind host led three friends and I inside to our table. We shuffled along in a single file line, placing our right hand on the right shoulder of the person in front, and praying that we didn&rsquo;t fall flat on our faces. Once at our table, the host grabbed my hand and placed it on what was allegedly a chair. I felt the entire thing up with both hands before trusting it enough to sit.</p>
<p>A few moments later, a blind waitress took our orders. As we waited for our drinks, we attempted to make sense of our surroundings. We called for each other&rsquo;s hands. We reached out to feel everything within arm&rsquo;s reach. There was a wall three feet to my left. Our table was square with a center beam securing it to the floor. There was plastic trim lining the edges of the table and an empty vase velcroed down in the center.</p>
<p>Our conversation focused on the experience at hand. Where do you think our table is in the cafe? Are your eyes opened or closed? How long do you think we&rsquo;ve been here?</p>
<p>During the conversation, I began to notice some unusual behavior in myself. For one, I wasn&rsquo;t facing whoever was speaking. There was no need for eye-contact. Instead, I leaned heavily towards the speaker with my ear. At one point, someone wondered aloud if they might be filming us with a black light camera. Before I had even processed the thought, I felt my posture straighten up.</p>
<p>Towards the end, my sense of hearing became heightened. The pace and tone of people&rsquo;s voices became much more pronounced. Without even trying, I was surprised by my awareness of how things were being said rather than simply what was said. It felt cool to have such a good grasp of what others were trying to convey.</p>
<p>Since leaving the cafe, I&rsquo;ve struggled to recreate that experience with my eyes open. It&rsquo;s amazing how one sense can affect your ability to make use of your others. I&rsquo;d heard about this effect but never experienced it for myself. If the next time you see me, and my eyes are closed. I&rsquo;m not sleeping. I&rsquo;m not meditating. I&rsquo;m listening.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Freshman Year</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/freshman-year/</link>
			<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/freshman-year/</guid>
			<description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been in Prague for 10 days now, and it feels like freshman year of college. It&amp;rsquo;s been both amazing and overwhelming. Upon arriving, they divided us among six hotels across the city. With everyone so excited to meet and become best friends, there was lots of energy in the air. And with beers costing a little over $1, there was plenty of social lubricant as well.
It&amp;rsquo;s been amazing to hear each person&amp;rsquo;s story about they heard about Remote Year and how they then mustered the courage to do it.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been in Prague for 10 days now, and it feels like freshman year of college. It&rsquo;s been both amazing and overwhelming. Upon arriving, they divided us among six hotels across the city. With everyone so excited to meet and become best friends, there was lots of energy in the air. And with beers costing a little over $1, there was plenty of social lubricant as well.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s been amazing to hear each person&rsquo;s story about they heard about Remote Year and how they then mustered the courage to do it. Many people&rsquo;s families weren&rsquo;t exactly supportive. Upon telling her about the program, one person&rsquo;s mom hung up on him. Another person&rsquo;s dad tried to tell her she couldn&rsquo;t go. With people from 15 countries and ages ranging from 22-50 years old, we have a good deal of diversity. There is one thing we have in common though. We were all willing to take a chance and try something different. This has created an immediate bond that&rsquo;s just so cool to be a part of.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s also been a bit overwhelming. I found myself trying a bit too hard to be outgoing and become friends with everyone. I needed to settle down, and I found an unexpected opportunity with some good old jet lag. At the time, my sleep schedule consisted of sleeping at 11pm, waking up at 2am, being wide awake until 6am, and then sleeping again until 10am. It sucked. After lying awake and allowing myself to get upset the first couple nights, I starting getting out of bed instead. Since I didn’t have anything I planned to do, I didn’t feel the usual pressure to hurry and get everything done.  My mind went quiet, and I found a calm that is often so difficult to find during the day. It was amazing how much I was able to get done when I wasn&rsquo;t worried about getting anything done at all.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Packing List</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/packing-list/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/packing-list/</guid>
			<description>For my year abroad, I&amp;rsquo;m attempting to travel light while staying prepared for different situations with regards to weather, laundry, pickpockets, etc. I did tons of research, but after just one day in Prague, I realized that it was mostly a waste. Months of googling was quickly trumped by one day of actual experience. On the bright side, with a duffel that&amp;rsquo;s literally the maximum size allowed for a carry-on, I was able to get by without checking any bags.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For my year abroad, I&rsquo;m attempting to travel light while staying prepared for different situations with regards to weather, laundry, pickpockets, etc. I did tons of research, but after just one day in Prague, I realized that it was mostly a waste. Months of googling was quickly trumped by one day of actual experience. On the bright side, with a duffel that&rsquo;s literally the maximum size allowed for a carry-on, I was able to get by without checking any bags.</p>
<p>![Empty Bags]({{ site.baseurl }}/images/Packing_EmptyBags.jpg)</p>
<p><strong>Bags:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Duffel - <em>Tom Bihn Aeronaut 45</em></li>
<li>Backpack - <em>Topo Designs Daypack</em></li>
</ul>
<p>![Clothes]({{ site.baseurl }}/images/Packing_Clothes.jpg)</p>
<p><strong>Clothes:</strong></p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>![Accessories]({{ site.baseurl }}/images/Packing_Accessories.jpg)</p>
<p><strong>Accessories:</strong></p>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>I stuffed all clothes and most accessories into the duffel. The laptop, books, and some smaller accessories were left for the backpack. Duffel ended up weighing 12+ kg, or more than 2 kg over the carry-on limit, but who&rsquo;s counting?</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Remote Year</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/remote-year/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/remote-year/</guid>
			<description>On June 1st, I&amp;rsquo;m leaving the country for a year. The plan is to spend one month in twelve different cities across the world. The trip includes 75 others and is organized by Remote Year. Here&amp;rsquo;s where we&amp;rsquo;ll be from June 2015 - May 2016:
 Prague, Czech Republic (Jun) Ljubljana, Slovenia (Jul) Cavtat, Croatia (Aug) Istanbul, Turkey (Sep) Penang, Malaysia (Oct) Ko Pha Ngan, Thailand (Nov) Hanoi, Vietnam (Dec) Kyoto, Japan (Jan) Buenos Aires, Argentina (Feb) Montevideo, Uruguay (Mar) Santiago, Chile (Apr) Lima, Peru (May)  When I describe my trip to friends, many respond initially out of fear, while others are able to respond with joy.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On June 1st, I&rsquo;m leaving the country for a year. The plan is to spend one month in twelve different cities across the world. The trip includes 75 others and is organized by <a href="http://remoteyear.com">Remote Year</a>. Here&rsquo;s where we&rsquo;ll be from June 2015 - May 2016:</p>
<ul>
<li>Prague, Czech Republic <em>(Jun)</em></li>
<li>Ljubljana, Slovenia <em>(Jul)</em></li>
<li>Cavtat, Croatia <em>(Aug)</em></li>
<li>Istanbul, Turkey <em>(Sep)</em></li>
<li>Penang, Malaysia <em>(Oct)</em></li>
<li>Ko Pha Ngan, Thailand <em>(Nov)</em></li>
<li>Hanoi, Vietnam <em>(Dec)</em></li>
<li>Kyoto, Japan <em>(Jan)</em></li>
<li>Buenos Aires, Argentina <em>(Feb)</em></li>
<li>Montevideo, Uruguay <em>(Mar)</em></li>
<li>Santiago, Chile <em>(Apr)</em></li>
<li>Lima, Peru <em>(May)</em></li>
</ul>
<p>When I describe my trip to friends, many respond initially out of fear, while others are able to respond with joy.</p>
<p>Fear:</p>
<ul>
<li>&ldquo;How do you think this will affect your career?&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Do you have travel insurance?&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Make sure to not drink the water.&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
<p>Joy:</p>
<ul>
<li>&ldquo;This is the best decision of your life.&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;I&rsquo;m so excited for you.&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Have all the fun in the world. This is the right thing to do.&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
<p>I get it. I&rsquo;m one of those people who watches a movie and worries about what terrible thing will happen next. When Reese Witherspoon was gently petting a horse in <em>Wild</em>, I wasn&rsquo;t appreciating the connection she was feeling towards her horse-loving mom. Instead, I was scared that the horse might snap and kick her.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Why Blog?</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/why-blog/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/why-blog/</guid>
			<description>This blog is both for me and you. By writing regularly, I hope to grow as a writer. More importantly, I hope to learn about myself, the world, and the people in it. Along the way, I hope to provide you with entertainment and perhaps some insight. Lots of hope.
I purposely kept the site&amp;rsquo;s design simple and bare. Without the bells and whistles of many websites, we can focus on the words.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog is both for me and you. By writing regularly, I hope to grow as a writer. More importantly, I hope to learn about myself, the world, and the people in it. Along the way, I hope to provide you with entertainment and perhaps some insight. Lots of hope.</p>
<p>I purposely kept the site&rsquo;s design simple and bare. Without the bells and whistles of many websites, we can focus on the words.</p>
<p>To kick things off, here&rsquo;s a quote from the late musician Margaret Young:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&lsquo;Often people attempt to live their lives backwards: they try to have more things, or more money, in order to do more of what they want so that they will be happier. The way it actually works is the reverse. You must first be who you really are, then do what you need to do, in order to have what you want.&rsquo; ~Margaret Young</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Back in the Rightful Hands</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/back-in-the-rightful-hands/</link>
			<pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/back-in-the-rightful-hands/</guid>
			<description>Amazing. Simply amazing. I never thought I could be so giddy for a Team USA victory. After Team USA defeated Spain 118-107, I was ecstatic. But why? It was supposed to happen, right? But, they did not blow the Spaniards out as most expected. Everything was set up for an easy USA win. Spain&amp;rsquo;s best ball handler and leader, Jose Calderon, was injured and unable to play. Then early in the game, one of USA&amp;rsquo;s biggest weaknesses was no longer.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Amazing. Simply amazing. I never thought I could be so giddy for a Team USA victory. After Team USA defeated Spain 118-107, I was ecstatic. But why? It was supposed to happen, right? But, they did not blow the Spaniards out as most expected. Everything was set up for an easy USA win. Spain&rsquo;s best ball handler and leader, Jose Calderon, was injured and unable to play. Then early in the game, one of USA&rsquo;s biggest weaknesses was no longer. They were knocking in threes from all angles. USA seemed destined for a blowout win and the gold medal finally back in their hands. But, Spain fought back. As the clock ticked towards zeros, the score somehow got closer and closer. Spain was within 4 with a few minutes remaining. It was not going to be easy. What did Team USA do? They inserted their best lineup and got the ball in the hands of their best players. Lebron made a critical layup and snagged some key rebounds. Dwyane Wade hit a big time three-pointer adding to his game-high 27 points. Kobe went off in his favorite quarter and scored 13 of his 20 points to go along with 6 assists and a memorable 4-point play.</p>
<p>The image above says it all. Team USA felt the same way I did. They were ecstatic. During the medal ceremony, they were giddy. And when our national anthem was played, they were at peace. USA basketball was at peace. The gold medal was back where it belonged.</p>
<p>There has been much debate about whether the &ldquo;Redeem Team&rdquo; could compete with or possibly defeat the &ldquo;Dream Team&rdquo; from the 1992 Olympics in Barcelona. I re-watched 2 games (Croatia and Angola) from the 1992 Olympics this past week along with the entire 2008 Olympics and exhibition games. I honestly do not know who would win.</p>
<p>The teams would attempt to establish their own vastly different styles of play. The Dream Team played an NBA style game. They did not run as much. They played half-court defense with limited pressure. They ran a half-court offense where they passed incredibly well but also iso&rsquo;d their players a considerable amount. The one place where the Dream Team would dominate is down low. David Robinson, Patrick Ewing, and Karl Malone would demolish Carlos Boozer, Dwight Howard and Chris Bosh. USA&rsquo;s lack of interior depth would be devastating. But, the Redeem team would make up for this with their punishing pressure defense and fast-break offense. The Redeem Team is unstoppable in the open court. Who would Larry Bird guard? In 1992, he was years past his prime and his bad back had pretty much given out on him. He could hardly stay in front of the Angola players. He would be a liability against the Redeem Team. Additionally, the Dream Team was never tested in 1992. They never had to fight back. Obviously, they had the players to do it, but they were never forced to do it collectively. The Redeem Team was forced and they succeeded.</p>
<p>In 1992, there were 3 international players in the NBA. A year ago, the NBA had 90 international players. The international scene has changed completely. Therefore, to try and look at the statistics or point differentials is useless.</p>
<p>The most interesting thing about the comparison is that it can actually be made. It has been 16 years since the Dream Team. In any kind of athletic competition, the best team of an era almost always will defeat the best team of 16 years prior. They quality of the game and the athletes simply progresses. The athletes are generally more skilled. They are bigger, faster, stronger, and quicker than their predecessors. The fact that most people and experts believe that the Dream Team would still defeat the Redeem Team shows you how great the Dream Team actually was. They were gods among boys during those Olympics.</p>
<p>Let us not try to figure out which team was better but just enjoy the truly magical shows they both displayed.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Gold Medal Game Preview</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/gold-medal-game-preview/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/gold-medal-game-preview/</guid>
			<description>Team USA has been sometimes inconsistent but mostly dominant on their way to the Gold Medal game.
  Kobe had a terrific offensive game versus Australia as the U.S. blew them out after a strong 3rd quarter.
  In the semi-final Argentina, Team USA came out strong leading by 20 after the first quarter. They put on cruise control somewhat but were in command throughout with Argentina only threatening once.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>
<p>Team USA has been sometimes inconsistent but mostly dominant on their way to the Gold Medal game.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Kobe had a terrific offensive game versus Australia as the U.S. blew them out after a strong 3rd quarter.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In the semi-final Argentina, Team USA came out strong leading by 20 after the first quarter. They put on cruise control somewhat but were in command throughout with Argentina only threatening once.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Luis Scola played the best game against the USA that anyone has played this Olympics. He was very sneaky and skillful underneath and Team USA had trouble containing him.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Now on to Spain. This will be the toughest game of the tournament.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I believe Spain held back somewhat in their group play game with USA, expecting to meet them again in the Gold Medal game.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It appears that their best guard, Jose Calderon, will miss the game. This severely diminishes Spain&rsquo;s already low chances of victory. But, they can pull it out if the USA cannot find their range and Spain plays almost perfectly.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Spain has the most talented team besides the USA and they match up decently (it&rsquo;s impossible for any team to match up well).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Lebron James is scary good. I cannot wait to see what he is going to be like in 4 years, the middle of his prime. He has the ability to be the best basketball player ever. If he develops a consistent jump shot and 3-ball, he will have no trouble scoring 100 points in a game.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I apologize for the lack of updates, but I just moved and it has been difficult to post. Will have another update following the Gold Medal game. I &lsquo;boldly&rsquo; predicted a gold medal for the USA earlier this month and I stand by that prediction.</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>USA vs. Greece Thoughts</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/usa-greece-thoughts/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/usa-greece-thoughts/</guid>
			<description>Best performance of the tournament by Team USA. That 2nd quarter was both dominant defensively and incredibly fun to watch.
  Dwyane Wade has been the team&amp;rsquo;s best player thus far. His energy off the bench sparked the 2nd quarter explosion. He competed spectacularly on both ends of the floor. Expended so much energy that he asked to come out of the game in the 2nd quarter. Clearly, Wade took the 2006 loss personal.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>
<p>Best performance of the tournament by Team USA. That 2nd quarter was both dominant defensively and incredibly fun to watch.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Dwyane Wade has been the team&rsquo;s best player thus far. His energy off the bench sparked the 2nd quarter explosion. He competed spectacularly on both ends of the floor. Expended so much energy that he asked to come out of the game in the 2nd quarter. Clearly, Wade took the 2006 loss personal. He had a determined look on his face all game.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The pick and roll defense was much improved from 2006. Chris Bosh defended superbly deflecting passes and hedging hard to prevent guard penetration.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Additionally, the overall half-court defense was much better. Less penetration was allowed and less wide open threes were given up. There is still room to improve.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Bosh is earning significant minutes due to his great touch around the basket and ability to finish after receiving contact. His feet on defense are also more active than Howard.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Team USA&rsquo;s free throw shooting was very poor (13-23) and is a concern going into their matchup with Spain.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The prime of Jason Kidd&rsquo;s career is over. He is no longer a top tier point guard. He will still be effective for a few more years, but he is no longer in top form. Regardless, he has had a terrific career and is one of the best PG&rsquo;s off all time.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Deron Williams had a few careless plays that makes me question his focus and commitment. He should watch how Dwyane Wade plays the game.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Next, USA battles Spain on Saturday Morning. Possible gold medal game preview.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Check out this spectacular play before NBC rips it down.</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>USA vs. Angola Thoughts</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/usa-angola-thoughts/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/usa-angola-thoughts/</guid>
			<description>First off, Team USA knowingly did not bring their A-game to this matchup. Coach K gave them the day before off to rest. Consequently, USA looked sloppy and unfocused at times throughout the game. No problem. The goal of Team USA is not to blow out every opponent. The goal is to win the Gold. They knew that even their worst game would probably be enough to defeat Angola.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>
<p>First off, Team USA knowingly did not bring their A-game to this matchup. Coach K gave them the day before off to rest. Consequently, USA looked sloppy and unfocused at times throughout the game. No problem. The goal of Team USA is not to blow out every opponent. The goal is to win the Gold. They knew that even their worst game would probably be enough to defeat Angola. Therefore, any serious analysis of their play in this game would not be very enlightening.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Kobe went 0-8 from 3-pt, but none were really bad shots. He is going to need to continue to take those open looks, but hopefully make a few more.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Angola took advantage of USA&rsquo;s continued poor 3-pt defense. This is one of Team USA&rsquo;s biggest weaknesses and will continue to be exposed as they face off against better teams in the next few days.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>TrueHoop noted that Chris Kaman might actually be a better 12th man off the bench than Carlos Boozer. Interesting to think about as Kaman suits up for Germany while holding American citizenship.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The next opponent, Greece, will be the roughest and most physical matchup for Team USA.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It appears as though Jason Kidd has become the de-facto starting PG. He plays for the first parts of both halves before Chris Paul and Deron Williams come in to play the major minutes. I think this is a great move by Coach K. It keeps Paul and Williams working hard and motivated to come back in 2012 as the next starting PG.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>During the final episode of ESPN&rsquo;s &lsquo;Road to Redemption&rsquo; series, Dwyane Wade stated that this is probably the last time that he, Lebron and Carmelo will play on the same team together. They have been together every summer since their rookie season. But, a split would be a major disappointment. In 2012, they will still be 3 of the best players in the world and will be needed for another pursuit at the gold. It looks like Team USA will field younger, inexperienced teams in the future and not be able to keep up with countries whose players play for them until they are no longer able.</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>USA vs. China Thoughts</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/usa-china-thoughts/</link>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/usa-china-thoughts/</guid>
			<description>The best part of the game was the classic NBA on NBC music; it gave me chills.
  The energy in that building was truly amazing. None of this year&amp;rsquo;s NBA Finals games contained that much excitement and anticipation. The energy did lessen as the lead grew but it was incredible to listen to and watch.
  I was not as excited as the national media was about Team USA&amp;rsquo;s performance.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul>
<li>
<p>The best part of the game was the classic NBA on NBC music; it gave me chills.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The energy in that building was truly amazing. None of this year&rsquo;s NBA Finals games contained that much excitement and anticipation. The energy did lessen as the lead grew but it was incredible to listen to and watch.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I was not as excited as the national media was about Team USA&rsquo;s performance. There are several areas in which the team needs to improve.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>With the speed and athleticism of the team, Coach K has emphasized pressure defense. Pressure defense does not mean gambling for deflections and steals on every possession. The pressure is intended to force the other team to cough up the ball. USA needs to apply pressure while staying in front of perimeter players and forcing them to make difficult shots.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Against China and in several of the exhibitions, USA gambled far too much, forcing other defenders to help out, resulting in wide open 3-pointers. Wade and Kobe have been the biggest culprits.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When USA is able to force turnovers and score in transition, they are unstoppable. But, if they run into a team that takes care of the ball and therefore slows the transition game, Team USA will have trouble. Their half court offense is inferior compared to many of these teams who have been playing together for several years.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The sustained effort level of the team was impressive, especially late in the game when the second unit played extended minutes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Dwight Howard&rsquo;s back-to-the-basket game is atrocious. He is very ineffective on offense when he is not dunking the ball. Andrew Bynum could be the starting center on this team in 2012.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The picture above depicts future Laker, Sun Yue, guarding his future teammate, Kobe Bryant. Yue was impressive versus the USA hitting some nice shots and showing no fear while challenging Kobe on a first half dunk.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>My late response to this game was the result of a busy weekend, but thoughts on the Angola game should also be up shortly.</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Off-Season Thoughts</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/off-season-thoughts/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/off-season-thoughts/</guid>
			<description>Now that the first official month of the NBA Off-Season has concluded, here are some thoughts:
  In the Elton Brand saga, I believe Mike Dunleavy and the Clippers when they say they had a verbal agreement with Brand. I also do not have a problem with Brand changing his mind and ditching the Clippers. That is the difference between a verbal agreement and a written one. Let&amp;rsquo;s remember that Brand tried to leave the Clippers once before.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now that the first official month of the NBA Off-Season has concluded, here are some thoughts:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>In the Elton Brand saga, I believe Mike Dunleavy and the Clippers when they say they had a verbal agreement with Brand. I also do not have a problem with Brand changing his mind and ditching the Clippers. That is the difference between a verbal agreement and a written one. Let&rsquo;s remember that Brand tried to leave the Clippers once before. Back in 2003, Brand (restricted free agent) signed an offer sheet with the Miami Heat. The Clippers matched the 6-year, 84 million dollar offer and retained Brand.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Nabbing Ron Artest was a great, albeit risky move by the Rockets. They have a relatively small window with their aging and injury prone stars, Yao and T-Mac. How will they balance the minutes of Shane Battier and Artest? Artest can defend multiple positions, but he is essentially a small forward (like Battier). The Rockets hope that Artest will contribute some on offense but still be able to defer to their true stars. Defensively, Artest is one of the best, but tends to occasionally lolly gag and take plays and even games off.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Warriors have been busy. First, they overpaid one of my favorite NBA players, Ronny Turiaf, with a 4 year, 17 million deal. Then, they overpaid Andris Biedrins. He is young and shows great promise, but was a restricted free agent. They could have waited to see what other teams offered or signed him to the one-year tender (making him unrestricted next season). No other team (NBA or Overseas) would have offered him near the 6 years, 63 million that he received.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Monta Ellis was also overpaid at 6 years, 66 million. He was featured in an unconventional Warriors offense that overvalued his performance. I think Ellis has the potential to be a star, but he has yet to prove he deserves that kind of money. Perhaps I am being too harsh on the Warriors, but you should understand that most NBA players are actually overpaid. We have a league currently with a very small number of teams under the salary cap. Most teams handcuffed themselves with long bloated contracts for players they thought to be their future. I respect a team like the Grizzlies for not maliciously spending their money and holding on to their cap space until they find the &ldquo;right&rdquo; players. Talent isn&rsquo;t everything in the NBA. You need &ldquo;winners.&rdquo;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Warriors also signed and overpaid Corey Maggette (5 yr., 50 mil.). Another player who is overpaid simply because of the ability to score points. He will continue to put up great scoring numbers for the Warriors, but he does not fit in their long-term plans. If they were indeed going to pay Ellis and Biedrins, they should have saved the rest of their money for a year like 2010 when Wade, LeBron, Bosh, and others will be available.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Warriors did well to obtain PG Marcus Williams from the Nets for a lottery-protected first round pick. Williams, a disappointment so far, has great potential.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>After making two grave mistakes in the past two off-seasons (Vladimir Radmanavic: 5 yr., 31 mil. and Luke Walton: 5 yr., 30 mil.), Mitch Kupchak did well this July. Radmanavic and Walton are both overpaid and figure to play very little for the Lakers next season. But this summer, Mitch chose not to match the Warriors' offer for Turiaf and convinced Sasha Vujacic to sign a shorter than desired 3 year deal worth 15 million.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Chicago Bulls made a good decision locking up Luol Deng (6 yr., 71 mil.), but I think they should be wary of offering Ben Gordon a long contract. With Rose as the PG of the future, Gordon is an undersized SG who should not be overpaid simply because he scores.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Joe Dumars is showing great patience in his desire to trade some of his core pieces. The Pistons should not rush into a hasty decision. I also like the Kwame Brown signing. Maybe 4 mil is a bit much, but 2 years is a good length and Brown has proved he can contribute when healthy (see 2006 Playoffs, not 2008 season).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Clippers stole a former defensive player of the year in Marcus Camby from the luxury-tax fearing Nuggets. Kaman and Camby together will work well, but the Clippers need to run next year with free-wheeling Baron Davis at the helm. I am not confident that Mike Dunleavy is the right man for the job there.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Celtics were smart not to offer James Posey a long deal. He will help some in New Orleans but is not worth the 4 year contract.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Another example of an overpaid signing: Mavericks signed DeSagana Diop to a 5 year, 32 million deal.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Lastly, Memphis Grizzlies' PG Marko Jaric is now engaged to supermodel, Adriana Lima (shown above).</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Who really is the greatest-of-all-time?</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/greatest-of-all-time/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/greatest-of-all-time/</guid>
			<description>We love to argue. The subject we argue about most is sports. One of the most commonly held debates is the comparison of athletes from different generations. Examples include: Kobe vs Jordan, Federer vs Sampras, Tiger vs Jack, and Peyton vs Montana. But, since these athletes did play during different eras, how can you really determine who was the better player?
For a lot of people, the answer is the numbers and/or statistics.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We love to argue. The subject we argue about most is sports. One of the most commonly held debates is the comparison of athletes from different generations. Examples include: Kobe vs Jordan, Federer vs Sampras, Tiger vs Jack, and Peyton vs Montana. But, since these athletes did play during different eras, how can you really determine who was the better player?</p>
<p>For a lot of people, the answer is the numbers and/or statistics. They argue that once Roger Federer wins more Grand Slams than Pete Sampras, Roger is the best of all time. They argue that once Tiger Woods wins more Majors than Jack Nicklaus, Tiger is the greatest golfer ever. They argue that since Michael Jordan has a higher scoring average and higher FG% than Kobe Bryant, Jordan is the better scorer. To determine who is the greatest at a particular sport, you have to establish criteria. The problem is that two people rarely agree on the correct criteria and waste most of their time bickering over it.</p>
<p>Take Michael Jordan, for instance. I believe him to be the greatest basketball player of all time. Most basketball fans agree. But what criteria are we using when making this claim? Perhaps it is that Jordan led the Bulls to 6 NBA Titles. Except, Bill Russell led his Celtics to 11 Titles&hellip;in 13 seasons! Neither the Celtics nor the Bulls had won a title before these two arrived. If not titles, how about the combination of regular season MVP awards and titles. Along with 6 titles, Jordan won 5 MVPs. Except, Bill Russell also won 5 MVPs and Kareem Abdul Jabbar won 6 MVPs to go along with his own 6 titles. Jordan also once won the Defensive Player of the Year award. Bill Russell won the award 10 times. If your criteria is most dominating player ever, then Jordan does not compare to Wilt Chamberlain who has four times as many 50+ point games as Jordan. Jordan is often called the most complete player ever, but take a look at Oscar Robertson. While Jordan&rsquo;s best season was 32.5 pts, 8 reb, and 8 asst; Oscar&rsquo;s best was 30.8 pts, 12.5 reb, 11.4 asst. Now, you may ask how Jordan is the greatest ever after falling short in all these arguments. The simple fact is that Jordan is the only player in each one of these arguments. He is in the conversation no matter which criteria you use. Is he the greatest player ever because of statistics and numbers? No. He is the greatest ever in spite of statistics and numbers.</p>
<p>The reason for this post was to look at how statisics have changed throughout the years. It is easy to see the change in a sport such as baseball. Home-run numbers skyrocketed in the &ldquo;steroid era,&rdquo; but have fallen almost as drastically since. To examine a less obvious change I took a look at the NBA&rsquo;s league statistics since 1980. I was shocked to see how much they had changed.</p>
<p>Note that 1999 lockout season was not included. Also 3 seasons in the 1990s with a shorter line were discarded for 3PT statistics.</p>
<p><strong>FG%</strong> - Peaked at 49.2% in 1984, low of 43.9% in 2004. Are defenses better or are players worse shooters? Coaching and scouting are definitely far more advanced.</p>
<p><strong>3PT</strong> - In 1981, 166 threes were attempted at 24.5%. In 2008, highs reached in both attempts (1485) and percentage (36.2%). Players attempt more threes each year.</p>
<p><strong>FT%</strong> - Remained fairly consistent through the years. High in 1989 (76.8%), low in 1994 (73.4%), and this past year was 75.5%.</p>
<p><strong>REB</strong> - Drastic variations here. Offensive rebounds highest in 1980 (1235) and lowest in 2007 (912). Defensive rebounds have increased in recent years to a high this past season (2524). Is this due to less effort on rebounding or better boxing out?</p>
<p><strong>ASST</strong> - Drastic decline from high in 1984 (2153) to low in 2006 (1690). Are players becoming more selfish or are statisticians less liberal about handing out assists?</p>
<p><strong>STL</strong> - Similar fall from high in 1980 (772) to low in 2006 (588). Are players better ball handlers or are defenders less aggressive?</p>
<p><strong>BLK</strong> - Fallen from high in 1984 (459) to low in 2007 (378).</p>
<p><strong>TOs</strong> - Declined from high in 1984 (1567) to low in 2008 (1157). See STL.</p>
<p><strong>PTS</strong> - High in 1986 (110.8); low in 2004 (93.4). Has risen since to 99.9 in 2008.</p>
<p><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/nitinsavant/InTheFridge?authkey=QPNEenzPeY4#5226298179654947618">Click for Full Excel Spreadsheet</a></p>
<p>How can you compare Magic Johnson&rsquo;s statistics of the 1980&rsquo;s with Chris Paul&rsquo;s statistics of today? You can&rsquo;t. They simply cannot be compared 1-to-1. The game has changed dramatically over the years. The average player is by far stronger and more athletic. The level of coaching and strategy has risen drastically. There have also been several rule changes instituted such as illegal defense and hand-checking. Teams such as the Phoenix Suns and Golden State Warriors have gone against conventional basketball wisdom and pushed the pace of the game to the limit. It also seems that the traveling violation is no longer called. Remarkable new talents such as Jordan, Shaq, and now Lebron drastically changed the way officials call games. So who really is the greatest? The answer to this question will always be an opinion, a judgment call. If Jordan played in today&rsquo;s era, would he still have achieved as much? If Shaq played during Wilt&rsquo;s era, what kinds of stats would he have produced? Not only has the physical makeup of the athletes changed over the years, but the numbers have too.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>#1 Player in Country Headed to Europe</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/top-player-europe/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/top-player-europe/</guid>
			<description>The #1 recruit in the country (according to Scout.com &amp;amp; ESPN.com) has decided to forego college and instead, play in Europe. He is the 2008 Naismith Male Player of the Year and Parade Magazine Player of the Year. Brandon Jennings, from Oak Hill Academy in Virginia, had intended to attend the University of Arizona for one season before declaring for the 2009 NBA Draft. But, he recently began to hesitate on this commitment.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The #1 recruit in the country (according to Scout.com &amp; ESPN.com) has decided to forego college and instead, play in Europe. He is the 2008 Naismith Male Player of the Year and Parade Magazine Player of the Year. Brandon Jennings, from Oak Hill Academy in Virginia, had intended to attend the University of Arizona for one season before declaring for the 2009 NBA Draft. But, he recently began to hesitate on this commitment. He had yet to receive a qualifying SAT score when he decided to take his talents to Europe instead of attending college. By foregoing college, Jennings will be able to hire an agent, play basketball year-round, sign endorsement deals, and play a significantly higher level of basketball.</p>
<p>Jennings' decision could spark interest in future youngsters at the opportunity to play in Europe rather than one year at the NCAA Division I level. Of course, that interest will depend upon the success or failure of Jennings in the next year. Brandon Jennings is an 18-year-old, 6'2&quot;, 165 lb point guard with incredible quickness and athletic ability. The crucial question is, how will he fair in Europe and how will it affect his future?</p>
<p>Jennings is a prototypical NBA point guard. He is known as a pass-first playmaker with good decision making, great ball handling, and excellent court vision. His weaknesses are strength and defense but both are common weaknesses at his age and will improve in time. One of Jennings' biggest dilemmas will be adapting to the European style of game. But the difficulties he endures will end up benefiting him immensely in the future. He will be playing in the most elite European leagues. In the past, the better players from these leagues have gone on to play very well in the NBA (Luis Scola, Juan Carlos Navarro). Unfortunately, the game will not come easy to Jennings. He will struggle with the different philosophies, different rules, and different offenses. Additionally, Jennings will not be playing against small, inferior high school kids anymore but instead, 25-35 year old mature men. If Jennings can learn how to mesh his current style of play with the European game, he will become a versatile and dynamic NBA point guard. Since Jennings could struggle mightily in the beginning, it could somewhat harm his 2009 draft stock. But, if Jennings is willing to accept the short-term risks, he will benefit from far greater rewards in the future.</p>
<p>This past year, 4 out of the top 5 picks in the draft were freshmen; overall, there were 10 freshmen selected in the first round. There will continue to be many freshmen drafted in the first round as long as the NBA continues the recently instituted one-year-rule. The rule requires players to be one year out of high school and at least 19 years of age to enter the draft. The rule has its advantages and disadvantages. As a basketball fan, it is tremendous. The NCAA season and March Madness have been spectacular in recent years with the additions of players such as Greg Oden, Kevin Durant, Derrick Rose, and Kevin Love. If not for the rule, all would have most likely proceeded directly to the NBA. The same advantages for the fans are advantages for the NCAA and the NBA. The NCAA makes hundreds of millions of dollars off their superstar &ldquo;student&rdquo; athletes. The NBA, in turn, benefits from free marketing of their future superstars. The problem is that the players, the main revenue generators, never get to touch any of the money. Freshmen are adults at 18 years old and should have the right to go professional and earn money for their services, right? Well, Jennings is making a push for that stance by signing a contract in Europe next season. He will make a generous amount of money.</p>
<p>Most of the media is knocking Jennings for his decision asserting that he has no idea what he is getting himself into. They say that he will struggle with the language and culture barriers. He will struggle with the tough practices in sometimes less than adequate facilities. The truth is that Jennings is an 18-year-old kid. He is supposed so struggle with these things. He is supposed to grow as a player and a person during this time in his life. If he is only going to be in college for one year anyways, why not go to a place where he can do the most growing up and do it the quickest. Journeying to a different country might be just what an 18-year-old future NBA star needs. In this day and age of spoiled, coddled NBA players, it would be in Jennings' best interest to avoid becoming just another immature, rich brat. The hardships he experiences while overseas will help him appreciate everything he earns once he does arrive in the NBA. When Jennings retires in 20 years as a perennial NBA All-Star, he will look at this decision as the best he ever made. He will be a better player, and more importantly, a better person, because of it.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>2002 WCF Game 6 vs. 2006 Finals Game 5</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/2002-wcf-vs-2006-finals/</link>
			<pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/2002-wcf-vs-2006-finals/</guid>
			<description>Now that the 2008 NBA Season has concluded, the remaining topics left to discuss are free agents, trades, and rumors all pertaining to next season. Before that begins, let&amp;rsquo;s revisit a controversial topic from the NBA&amp;rsquo;s recent history. Last summer, NBA referee Tom Donaghy came under investigation by the FBI for allegedly point shaving and altering the outcome of NBA games in which he refereed. During the last year, there has been considerable evidence gathered that shows the scores of the games he refereed to be consistent with point shaving.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now that the 2008 NBA Season has concluded, the remaining topics left to discuss are free agents, trades, and rumors all pertaining to next season. Before that begins, let&rsquo;s revisit a controversial topic from the NBA&rsquo;s recent history. Last summer, NBA referee Tom Donaghy came under investigation by the FBI for allegedly point shaving and altering the outcome of NBA games in which he refereed. During the last year, there has been considerable evidence gathered that shows the scores of the games he refereed to be consistent with point shaving. In addition, Donaghy has confessed to the accusation and provided the FBI with many details about his exploits. In one of Donaghy&rsquo;s statements to the FBI, he claimed that the NBA &ldquo;fixed&rdquo; an important playoff game by appointing &ldquo;company men&rdquo; to officiate the game. The game in question was Game 6 of the 2002 Western Conference Finals between the Los Angeles Lakers and the Sacramento Kings. Next to this game, the next most controversially officiated game in recent history occurred in the 2006 NBA Finals between the Dallas Mavericks and Miami Heat. Let&rsquo;s take an in-depth look at both games in question.</p>
<p><strong>2002 WCF Game 6</strong> &ndash; The Kings defeated the Lakers in Game 5 to establish a 3-2 series lead heading back to Los Angeles for Game 6. The Lakers ended up sending the series back to Sacramento behind a 106-102 victory. The controversy exists in a 27-9 advantage in free throws for the Lakers in the hotly contested 4th quarter. Conspiracy theorists believe that the NBA fixed the game in order to extend the series to seven games. Reasons for the fix are stated to be primarily financially motivated. A 7th game would mean more money for the NBA. Also, a big-market team like the Lakers going to the NBA Finals also equals more money for the NBA. The Lakers went on to an overtime victory in Game 7 before sweeping the New Jersey Nets for their third consecutive NBA title.</p>
<p><strong>2006 Finals Game 5</strong> &ndash;The Miami Heat defeated the Dallas Mavericks 101-100 in a dramatic overtime game in Miami giving the Heat a 3-2 series advantage. The controversy here is that eventual Finals MVP, Dwyane Wade, was given 25 free throw attempts in the game, the same amount as the entire Mavericks team. The Heat as a team were awarded 49 free throw attempts. Wade shot 11 for 28 from the field in route to 43 points including game winning free throws with 1.9 seconds left on the clock. The foul called with 1.9 seconds has been deemed very questionable by most observers especially since it was called by a referee (Bennett Salvatore) who was not in position to make the call. The Heat went on to win the NBA title in six games.</p>
<p>There have been numerous opinions formed about these two games from fans and the media throughout the country. NBA games are the hardest games to officiate in professional sports and by simply watching a game, it is almost impossible to definitively determine if the game was fixed or not. Roland Beech of 82games.com has performed a very impressive in-depth analysis of every call made during the two games in question. Beech is a very well respected student of the game who covers the NBA with an intense statistical focus. 82games.com is a tremendous site with loads of unconventional and insightful statistics about NBA teams and players. Since Beech&rsquo;s analysis is very extensive, I will summarize his data and conclusions while providing commentary. Beech took an analytical approach in which he reviewed every call made in each game and determined whether the call was correct, probably correct, 50/50, dubious, or very dubious. He also grouped the calls by the referees. In this way, it can be determined if a team received favorable calls and if a particular referee favored a team</p>
<p><strong>2002 WCF Game 6</strong> &ndash; The referees were Dick Bavetta, Bob Delaney, and Ted Bernhardt. The overall calls favor L.A. barely (55-54). The calls of the individual officials do not really jump out. The largest margin is Bavetta favoring the Lakers (20-15). The one thing that jumps out is that the dubious and very dubious calls favor L.A. (7-2). This is a significant discrepancy and gives argument to Kings Fans that someone was out to get them. Since it is not exactly straightforward to determine how many points each call results in, Beech came up with a &lsquo;Points Impact&rsquo; method. Using the method, he concluded that the Lakers received a net bonus of 6 points from favorable calls. The Lakers ended up winning by 4 points.</p>
<p><strong>2006 Finals Game 5</strong> &ndash; The referees were Bennett Salvatore, Joey Crawford, and Joe DeRosa. The overall calls favor Miami (50-38). The thing that jumps out the most in this game is that Salvatore&rsquo;s calls favored Miami drastically (25-11). Of the other refs, Crawford favored Dallas (17-11) and DeRosa favored Miami (18-12). Another thing that jumps out is the dubious and very dubious calls which favor Miami (5-1). If you throw in the 50/50 calls, the discrepancy is still high (13-5). It should be mentioned that Salvatore also whistled Avery Johnson for a technical foul during the game. Using the &lsquo;Points Impact&rsquo; method, Beech concluded that Miami received a net bonus of 6 points from their favorable calls. The 6 points is very significant in an overtime game but not nearly as significant as the free throw disparity (49-25) could have suggested.</p>
<p><strong>2002 WCF Game 6</strong> &ndash; The Lakers did benefit from a 40-24 free throw advantage, but if you take out intentional fouls, the discrepancy is only 34-24. Additionally, the Lakers were clearly the more aggressive offensive team. The Kings' offense was far more perimeter based therefore you would normally expect a free throw advantage for the Lakers. Additionally, the Lakers were on their home court. As much as the NBA might like to deny it, statistics and the naked-eye show that referees tend to give the benefit of the doubt to the home team on tough calls. This is a MAJOR problem in the NBA. Referees are paid to be impartial and they should be trained to be affected as little as possible by the home crowd. Home teams should not be given an advantage. Unfortunately, the NBA has been favorable to the home team for years and will continue to be. Many Laker fans will point to Game 5 of the same series when the Kings received many favorable calls down the stretch to pull out a close win in Sacramento.</p>
<p><strong>2006 Finals Game 5</strong> &ndash; The same offensive aggressiveness argument can be made in this game. Wade drove to the basket hard countless times and with him and Shaq, Miami was clearly the more aggressive offensive team. The final play of the game has been scrutinized by many fans and analysts. There are claims of a backcourt violation on Wade, two possible offensive fouls on Wade, carrying violation on Wade, and then the eventual foul call for Wade against Dirk Nowitzki. All the possible calls against Wade were overlooked while a foul for him was called. In my opinion, all the calls should have been no calls and the players should have decided the game unless there was a blatant foul. The fact is that none of the calls were obvious and should not have been made. The call that was made was overlooked by baseline official, Crawford, and called by Salvatore from near mid-court. I do not believe the officiating of a game should change in the final seconds but I also think it is inevitable. In any sport or competition that requires judgment calls: As the stakes rise, the game changes.</p>
<p>Of course, all of this analysis could be completely bogus. The referees do not completely control what calls they make. Certain refs are put in positions to make certain calls depending on what part of the court they are covering. In any one NBA game, there are thousands of different intricacies that can affect the outcome of the game. The data presented by 82games.com is the most extensive data that is available on any one NBA game that is open to the public. So take from it what you must. Draw your own conclusions.</p>
<p>Do I think the games were fixed? Absolutely not. Do I think the NBA told their &ldquo;company men&rdquo; to give more favorable calls to a particular team? Nope. The games were simply a result of some poor officiating. If you asked me which game was more poorly officiated, I would say the Mavs-Heat game. The call discrepancy of Bennett Salvatore is pretty ridiculous and although it is possible to be just a coincidence, it will be forever questioned.</p>
<p><strong>For 82games.com&rsquo;s full analysis:</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://www.82games.com/lakerskingsgame6.htm">2002 WCF Game 6</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.82games.com/game5refs.htm">2006 Finals Game 5</a></p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>2008 NBA Draft Review</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/nba-draft-review/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/nba-draft-review/</guid>
			<description>The NBA Draft is one of my favorite times of the year. Each and every potential draftee is thoroughly scrutinized and dissected in every which way. Teams literally use hundreds of complex statistical algorithms to try to determine who to pick. Teams find out what each draftee does with their free time and who he hangs out with. No detail goes unnoticed or unconsidered. From the moment the player declares until the day of the draft, every move the player makes is noted and analyzed.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The NBA Draft is one of my favorite times of the year. Each and every potential draftee is thoroughly scrutinized and dissected in every which way. Teams literally use hundreds of complex statistical algorithms to try to determine who to pick. Teams find out what each draftee does with their free time and who he hangs out with. No detail goes unnoticed or unconsidered. From the moment the player declares until the day of the draft, every move the player makes is noted and analyzed. BUT&hellip;once the draft occurs, all the hoopla ends. You will not hear about most of the draft picks for years. At that point, some draft picks will be re-evaluated and labeled as &ldquo;studs,&rdquo; and some labeled as &ldquo;busts.&rdquo; But, most of the draft picks will never again find themselves as popular as they were for these couple months.</p>
<p>The 2008 NBA Draft was quite eventful. Before I reveal my thoughts, a little background on this draft. Almost every team in the draft says that it is one of the most difficult drafts ever to predict. Different teams are coming to drastically dissimilar conclusions on all sorts of players. Therefore, I did not attempt to preview or mock the draft, but I will review it. One of the common mistakes made in drafting is drafting for need or position rather than simply taking the BPA (best player available). For a simple example of this mistake, see the 1984 Draft and some guy named MJ. Another mistake is the best-case scenario mistake. Too many fans, and some teams, evaluate players based on their best-case scenarios. Teams draft the player with the highest potential or upside. Instead, teams should more heavily value which players have the best chance of reaching their best-case scenarios. These are the players with the strongest character and best work ethics.</p>
<p>Now, I will go through the lottery picks and give my thoughts focusing on the players that I saw play the most and therefore know the most about. Then I will add thoughts on a few post-lottery picks that I liked.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Bulls - Derrick Rose</strong> &ndash; Easy no-brainer pick. Hall-of-fame potential. Great teammate.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Heat - Michael Beasley</strong> &ndash; Another easy no-brainer pick. Hollinger&rsquo;s #1 guy by a mile.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Wolves - O.J. Mayo</strong> &ndash; Grizzlies end up getting Mayo, the guy they wanted badly. Mayo is going to be a solid NBA player, no doubt. But it remains to be seen if he can be a star.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Sonics - Russell Westbrook</strong> &ndash; Shocker of the draft going this early. Best 1-on-1 defender in the draft. Long, fast, and athletic. Perfect complement for Durant if he can develop into a PG. Decent jumper and ball-handling but must improve upon both. Gets into the lane and finishes easily. All-NBA Defensive 1st Team potential.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Grizzlies - Kevin Love</strong> &ndash; The most risk-free pick in the draft. Great grab by the Wolves along with Mike Miller. Love has the highest basketball IQ in the draft. Can shoot, rebound, pass extremely well. Mentally and physically tough. Extremely strong. More athletic than people think. Improved defense immensely under Ben Howland last season. Potentially an NBA All-Star, but no chance at being a bust.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Knicks - Danilo Gallinari</strong> &ndash; I respect Donnie Walsh and the Knicks for choosing the BPA, instead of trying to appease the fans. Do not know much about him except from watching some YouTube highlight videos.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Clippers - Eric Gordon</strong> &ndash; Have not seen him play much. Known as a great shooter (even though stats disagree) and a solid defender. Small for a SG.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Bucks - Joe Alexander</strong> &ndash; My least favorite pick of the draft. Passing on Lopez and Bayless is puzzling. Tough, very athletic combo forward, but needs to improve skills in all facets.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Bobcats - D.J. Augustin</strong> &ndash; Risky pick with Lopez and Bayless STILL on the board. More of a Steve Nash type PG who can shoot, pass, and penetrate. Small in size and cannot defend very well. Good leader.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Nets - Brook Lopez</strong> &ndash; Lopez finally picked. Steal for Nets. Lopez (with limited athleticism) has potential to be a bust, but his combination of size, length and skilll is promising.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Pacers - Jerryd Bayless</strong> &ndash; Steal of the first round. Bayless traded to Blazers. The Blazers are scary good, and their GM looks like the best in the business these days.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Kings - Jason Thompson</strong> &ndash; Confusing, but gutsy pick, could have traded down and gotten him. Put up great numbers at a small school (Rider). Big NBA Frame that he needs to grow into.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Blazers - Brandon Rush</strong> &ndash; Traded to Pacers. Like the pick. Think more athletic Aaron Afflalo.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Warriors - Anthony Randolph</strong> &ndash; Similar player to Brandan Wright. Freak athlete. At least three years away from being any kind of productive.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Nets - Ryan Anderson</strong> &ndash; He can flat out score. Led Pac-10 in scoring.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Hornets - Darrell Arthur</strong> &ndash; If healthy, one of the steals of the draft. Traded to Grizzlies.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Wolves - Mario Chalmers</strong> &ndash; Biggest steal of the draft. Quick and heady point guard who can defend the ball and cause chaos on defense. Shot 47% from 3-point range. Takes care of the ball and runs the offense well. Traded to Heat. Chalmers-Wade-Marion-Beasley core is dangerous in East (in a couple years).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Clippers - DeAndre Jordan</strong> &ndash; #1 overall pick type athleticism. Would have been top 5 pick out of high school. Disappointing freshman season, but was still projected lottery early on. Could become a dominant force if he develops a work ethic and passion for the game. Low risk, high reward pick for the Clippers.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Bucks - L.R. Mbah a Moute</strong> &ndash; Terrific defender. Think James Posey without a jump shot. Can guard several positions. Will be in the league a long time simply because he plays hard and dominates defensively.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Nets - Chris Douglas Roberts</strong> &ndash; Richard Hamilton clone who can also flat out score.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Wizards - Bill Walker</strong> &ndash; Top 10 talent, but has suffered from bad advice and some knee injuries. If healthy, potential All-Star. Traded to Celtics.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Draft Winners</strong>:
<strong>Heat</strong> &ndash; Chalmers and Beasley were both easy picks, but the easy pick is not always made.
<strong>Celtics</strong> &ndash; Giddens and Walker are both athletic guys who can contribute off the bench when Pierce and Allen are resting.
<strong>Bulls</strong> &ndash; Derrick Rose.
<strong>Pacers</strong> &ndash; Hibbert and Rush are solid, experienced winners who will have long NBA careers (albeit as role players).
<strong>Clippers</strong> &ndash; Solid pick with Gordon, possible superb draft if Jordan turns out.
<strong>Sonics</strong> and <strong>Wolves</strong> &ndash; Just because I like Westbrook and Love so much.
<strong>Nets</strong> &ndash; Got great value at their picks with Lopez, Anderson and CDR.
<strong>Blazers</strong> &ndash; Stole Bayless. They have been on the draft winners list for many consecutive years now.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Olympics Preview</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/olympics-preview/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/olympics-preview/</guid>
			<description>The 2008 Summer Olympics kick off August 8th, 2008 in Beijing, China. The biggest story among American sports is the U.S.&amp;rsquo;s Men&amp;rsquo;s Basketball Team&amp;rsquo;s attempt to win their first Olympic gold medal since 2000. Before I get into the makeup and potential of this year&amp;rsquo;s team, let&amp;rsquo;s review the failures of the past 8 years. After winning their third consecutive gold medal in 2000, the team lost their first international game at the 2002 World Championships since using strictly NBA players.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The 2008 Summer Olympics kick off August 8th, 2008 in Beijing, China. The biggest story among American sports is the U.S.&rsquo;s Men&rsquo;s Basketball Team&rsquo;s attempt to win their first Olympic gold medal since 2000. Before I get into the makeup and potential of this year&rsquo;s team, let&rsquo;s review the failures of the past 8 years. After winning their third consecutive gold medal in 2000, the team lost their first international game at the 2002 World Championships since using strictly NBA players. The Americans finished a shocking 6th in the World.</p>
<p>In 2004, the team journeyed to Athens composed of a group of very inexperienced, young players. Notables on the team were veterans Tim Duncan and Allen Iverson, but also the youngsters Lamar Odom, Shawn Marion, Richard Jefferson, Stephon Marbury, Carlos Boozer, Lebron James, and Carmelo Anthony. In the quarterfinals, the team squeaked by a Spain team composed of Pau Gasol (29 pts) and future NBA players, Jose Calderon and Juan Carlos Navarro. After defeating Spain by 8, the Americans lost to Argentina by 8 in the semifinals. The Argentina team composed of Manu Ginobili, Carlos Delfino, and Andres Nocioni had their way against the porous American defense. Argentina went on to win the Gold defeating Italy by 15.</p>
<p>Following the 2004 debacle, the U.S. committee replaced head coach Larry Brown with Duke Head coach, Mike Krzyzewski. In 2006 led by Krzyzewski, the U.S. team won the Bronze medal again after losing to Greece, a team with no NBA players. Spain subsequently pummeled Greece to win the Gold; Pau Gasol was named MVP of the tournament. A second consecutive bronze medal earned James the nickname &lsquo;Lebronze.&rsquo; Another horrible failure motivated many NBA players to dedicate themselves to returning U.S. basketball to where it belongs. The major addition to the U.S. team was current NBA MVP Kobe Bryant. Kobe led the team to the FIBA Americas Championships in the Summer of 2007. The team coasted to a Gold medal; they dominated opponents by going 10-0 with an average margin of victory of 39.5 pts per game. The team defeated Argentina twice en route to the gold medal. Kobe was one of the standout performers of the tournament locking down the tournament&rsquo;s leading scorer Leandro Barbosa (22 ppg) and holding him to 4 pts.</p>
<p>Now let&rsquo;s get to this year&rsquo;s squad:</p>
<p><em>Point Guards</em>:</p>
<p><strong>Jason Kidd</strong> – oldest player on team by far (35), not the best PG on the team, but provides necessary leadership and experience</p>
<p><strong>Chris Paul</strong> – best PG in the NBA, but has very limited international experience</p>
<p><strong>Deron Williams</strong> – tough, rugged player who is also the best shooter of the trio</p>
<p><em>Shooting Guards</em>:</p>
<p><strong>Kobe Bryant</strong> – second oldest player (29); will guard opposing team&rsquo;s best perimeter player; significantly less pressure to produce on offense compared to on Lakers</p>
<p><strong>Dwyane Wade</strong> – coming off injury-plagued season; his effectiveness is uncertain</p>
<p><strong>Michael Redd</strong> – possibly team&rsquo;s premier shooter but is coming off his worst shooting NBA season in years</p>
<p><em>Small Forwards</em>:</p>
<p><strong>Lebron James</strong> – should be able to physically dominate and manhandle opponents as he does in the NBA; his superior passing ability is a big attribute from the small forward position</p>
<p><strong>Tayshaun Prince</strong> – selected as 12th man over Tyson Chandler; probably will only play in blowouts unless team suffers significant injuries, but if needed can defend practically all 5 positions</p>
<p><em>Power Forwards</em>:</p>
<p><strong>Carmelo Anthony</strong> – playing out of position, but has the size to guard and rebound against most international PF&rsquo;s; quickness and versatility will benefit team on offense</p>
<p><strong>Carlos Boozer</strong> – toughest guy on team; I worry he will be in constant foul trouble similar to Tim Duncan in 2004</p>
<p><em>Centers</em>:</p>
<p><strong>Dwight Howard</strong> – freakish athletic ability should allow him to dominate opposing centers on both ends of the floor; also must stay out of foul trouble</p>
<p><strong>Chris Bosh</strong> – FT shooting ability (84%) could provide him minutes in the clutch</p>
<p>As can be seen, the players that played significant minutes in Athens are all gone. The young guys, Carmelo, Lebron, and Boozer did not play much in Athens but received valuable experience as well as the agony of losing. The starting lineup will be the same as it was last year at the FIBA Americas: Kidd, Kobe, Lebron, Carmelo, and Howard. This lineup has it all: Leadership, Passing, Toughness, Rebounding, Athleticism, and Strength. If teams are sagging off of Kidd and Lebron, Coach Krzyzewski can insert Williams and Redd to create a deadly three-point shooting lineup. There are no glaring weak links on defense on the squad, perhaps Boozer against quick PF&rsquo;s. There are several teams the Americans need to worry about it. Of course the defending gold medalists Argentina will be very tough. Additionally China, with a healthy Yao Ming and youngster Yi Jianlian, could provide matchup problems along with the raucous home crowd they&rsquo;ll bring every game. Carlos Arroyo leads a deceptively tough Puerto Rican team and Spain has quite a few experienced NBA players led by Pau Gasol. The U.S. is in a tough round robin group which includes China and Spain.</p>
<p>I believe this team will coast to the semifinals where they will meet some challenge but eventually win the final two games and return the Gold medal to U.S. soil. The differences in this team compared to the 2004 team are vast. The major difference is the strength and athleticism. The guys that played major minutes in Athens, Iverson, Duncan, Odom, Jefferson, and Marbury have been replaced by Kobe, Wade, Lebron, Carmelo, Howard, Williams. The U.S. team needs to use their athleticism and strength to physically dominate their opponents while staying out of foul trouble. International rules are different; they cannot expect fouls called in the NBA to translate to international play. The next major difference is the point guard play. The score-first mentalities of Iverson and Marbury have been replaced by the pass-first mentalities of Kidd, Paul, and Williams. The last key difference is the commitment to defense. Kobe displayed this commitment emphatically last year at FIBA. The team has the ability to lock down any team in the World and if they can commit to this, they will win the Gold medal.</p>
<p>I tried to keep this post shorter even though I had a lot more detail that could have been included. Draft Review will be up next following this Thursday&rsquo;s exciting NBA Draft.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Part of the Family</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/part-of-the-family/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/part-of-the-family/</guid>
			<description>I just watched a Lakers 07-08 Season Tribute video. The video inspired me. The Lakers have had an incredible season. Phil Jackson did a remarkable job at managing this Lakers&#39; squad. A criticism of Jackson in the past was that he could not teach and groom younger players. You can throw that theory out the window. Now, the theory is that Phil got thoroughly outcoached by Doc Rivers in the Finals.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just watched a Lakers 07-08 Season Tribute video. The video inspired me. The Lakers have had an incredible season. Phil Jackson did a remarkable job at managing this Lakers' squad. A criticism of Jackson in the past was that he could not teach and groom younger players. You can throw that theory out the window. Now, the theory is that Phil got thoroughly outcoached by Doc Rivers in the Finals. Practically every analyst and a lot of Laker fans think so. I do not. Is there a possibility that the Celtics were so much better than the Lakers that no matter what Phil did, the Celtics were going to win. I am not saying that Phil did not make mistakes during the Finals and also, there is no excuse for getting manhandled by 40 in the final game. But, Phil did an incredible job coaching the Lakers throughout the season and through Western Conference. The fans that are calling for his firing are completely unfounded and out of touch. Phil is one of the best coaches in the NBA and the perfect coach for this Laker team. For those of you who believe that Paul Pierce completely outplayed Kobe Bryant during the series, here are some statistics, Kobe: 26 ppg, 5 asst, 5 reb, 3 stl, 41%FG. Pierce: 22 ppg, 6 asst, 5 reb, 1 stl, 43%FG. Better numbers yes, but not by much; not to mention Pierce went up against the Lakers' defense which is laughably inferior to the Celtics&rsquo;s. Let us be reminded that Lebron James shot 35%FG in his series against the Celtics.</p>
<p>Now let&rsquo;s get to the real subject of this article. Kobe. During the playoffs many fans and analysts began comparing Kobe to the one and only Michael Jordan. And then when the Lakers lost to the Celtics, the tune changed to &lsquo;Can we stop comparing him to Michael now?&rsquo; The truth is that Kobe himself does not want to be compared to Jordan. Kobe wants to be so much better than Jordan that people do not dare compare Jordan to him. In my opinion, Kobe is a better scorer than Jordan. Kobe is the most talented offensive player in the history of the game. He has it all. He can shoot from almost unlimited range and if he drives the paint, he has every shot, layup, and dunk in the book. In fact, Kobe has rewritten the book. Let&rsquo;s get one thing straight, I am not saying Kobe is a better player than Jordan. The fact is that you cannot accurately compare players from different eras. The best way you can compare them is to compare their performance relative to their era. The problem with this is that certain players play in easier eras than others. If Jordan were in his prime during the 1980s of Magic Johnson and Larry Bird, would he have 6 rings? If Magic or Larry were not both around during the 1980&rsquo;s, how many rings would the other one of them have? This is a valid argument but still a weak one. You cannot punish Michael for dominating his competition and also, who is to say that he would not have won 6 titles in any era.</p>
<p>Kobe is 29 years old. Kobe has five finals appearances and three titles. When Jordan was 29, he had two finals appearances and two titles. Can we please wait until Kobe&rsquo;s career is over before we say whether or not he was a better player than Jordan? I guess not. So let&rsquo;s go for it. If you have not yet realized it, I am going to defend Kobe. First off, Kobe has to face zone defenses (which is pretty much what the Celtics played). In Jordan&rsquo;s era, zoning was illegal. Secondly, everyone underestimates just how good Scottie Pippen was. He is one of the 50 greatest players of all time, 10x All-Defensive Team selection, 3x All-NBA First Team selection, and 7x NBA All-Star. During the six title years of the Bulls, here are Pippen&rsquo;s assist averages: 6.2, 7.0, 6.3, 5.9, 5.7, 5.8. Here are Jordan&rsquo;s averages: 5.5, 6.1, 5.5, 4.3, 4.3, 3.5. Pippen led the Bulls in assists in each of those years. If you look at the playoff stats during those years, Pippen led the Bulls in assists in four out of the six title runs. The fact is that Jordan was not always the primary playmaker on the Bulls. Pippen usually created more shots for his teammates than Jordan did. You will not find one year since Shaq left that Kobe has not led the Lakers in assists. Additionally, the quality of Jordan&rsquo;s supporting casts is very misconstrued. In the 1993-94 season, the year after Jordan first retired, the Bulls won 55 games and lost in 7 games to the Knicks in the conference semifinals, led by Scottie Pippen. The Bulls were always one of the league&rsquo;s best defenses. They had perfect role players around Jordan who made open shots and played tough defense. Just because they did not put up great offensive numbers does not mean they were not good. Average basketball fans make the error of only looking at offensive statistics to determine a player&rsquo;s worth. If this was true, guys like Bruce Bowen, James Posey, and Ronny Turiaf would not have jobs.</p>
<p>Here is an excerpt from J.A. Adande&rsquo;s ESPN article: &ldquo;Do you think Jordan never had a Finals performance with numbers like the 27 points and 42 percent shooting Bryant&rsquo;s experiencing against the Celtics? You must not have watched the 1996 Finals, when Jordan averaged 27 points and shot 42 percent against Seattle.&rdquo;</p>
<p>When Jordan played in the NBA, he was the NBA&rsquo;s darling child. He resurrected the NBA after Bird and Magic left. He alone was making hundreds of millions of dollars for the NBA. If you can believe that the NBA has a conspiracy theory for the Lakers and Celtics to meet in the Finals now, there is no way you cannot believe the NBA wanted Jordan to succeed back then. I, myself, am not a believer in any kind of conspiracy theory about the NBA. As Los Angeles Times writer Mark Heisler put it, &ldquo;If the NBA is fixing anything, it&rsquo;s doing a really lousy job.&rdquo; Anyways, in those days, Jordan got every call. Any time he drove the lane, he either scored or got a foul. If you watched this year&rsquo;s Lakers series between the Spurs or the Celtics, you can see that the same was not true for Kobe. Magic once told Larry Bird not to stand too close to Michael or they might call a foul.</p>
<p>As for their troubles off the court, everyone is familiar with Kobe&rsquo;s rape accusation in Colorado. The charges were dropped shortly after the trial began. The truth might never be known, but we do know that Kobe committed Adultery. Shocking right, except Jordan did the same….many times. Jordan cheated on his wife numerous times during their marriage and has a former mistress that claims that Jordan promised her $5 million when he retired to keep her quiet. Additionally, Jordan&rsquo;s gambling problems are well known as he once lost $57,000 on golf, poker, and other gambling and then lied about it. My point is that many NBA stars have off-court troubles. You cannot let those issues cloud your thinking when you evaluate them as basketball players. Both Jordan and Kobe have tried mightily to resurrect their images and become respectable role models. I respect both immensely.</p>
<p>Another argument I want to explore is the Tiger Woods comparison. I heard this on ESPN and was dumbfounded at how ESPN discovered another way to criticize Kobe by saying he is not even close to Tiger. Why the heck would you even compare the two? Forget the fact that their sports are not even close to similar. Tiger plays an individual sport. He does not have to work with teammates, encourage teammates, or make his teammates better. He simply has to make himself better. If basketball were an individual sport, Kobe would be the greatest of All-Time. The man scored 81 points in a game. Tiger and Kobe both have personality flaws that are geared towards individual accomplishments. They care about themselves above all others. Tiger did not care about the feel good story of Rocco Mediate last weekend, he wanted to crush him. Kobe cannot behave in this way, therefore he has had to adjust. He learned how to work with his coach and his teammates and has made great strides. Is he perfect? No… not even close. But he is trying hard and that is all one can ask.</p>
<p>Finally, this is to all the Laker and Kobe haters. I love the Lakers and therefore I love Kobe. I am a Laker fan BEFORE I am a Kobe fan. The Lakers are my family and Kobe is part of that family. I treat Kobe like a brother. Sometimes your brother misbehaves and makes mistakes, but you love your brother regardless. I will never argue that Kobe is not sometimes selfish, arrogant, condescending, self-absorbed, or annoying. But he is a brother and a son to Laker fans and as long as he is part of the Laker family, we will support him.</p>
<p>Here is the inspirational video I spoke of: <a href="http://www.lakersmedia.com/?p=176#more-176">http://www.lakersmedia.com/?p=176#more-176</a></p>
<p>Video of Kobe against Zone Defenses: <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4kYBeNQdSCc">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4kYBeNQdSCc</a></p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Final Thoughts on the Finals</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/final-finals-thoughts/</link>
			<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/final-finals-thoughts/</guid>
			<description>The 6th and final game of the NBA Finals ended sluggishly with the Boston Celtics&#39; 39 point thrashing of the Los Angeles Lakers Tuesday night in Boston. I had originally planned on waiting a couple days before expressing my thoughts about the game, the series, and the season, but to my surprise, I recovered from the loss rather quickly. During the middle of the third quarter, it began to hit me that the season was over.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The 6th and final game of the NBA Finals ended sluggishly with the Boston Celtics' 39 point thrashing of the Los Angeles Lakers Tuesday night in Boston. I had originally planned on waiting a couple days before expressing my thoughts about the game, the series, and the season, but to my surprise, I recovered from the loss rather quickly. During the middle of the third quarter, it began to hit me that the season was over. The most tumultuous season in Lakers history was over. I had been preparing myself for this inevitable end since after Game 4. That night was far more emotionally draining than tonight.</p>
<p>The blowout helped. There was no doubt. The Celtics were the better team and that got me thinking. Why were the Lakers so heavily picked by the ‘experts’ to win the series? I found that the reason is the same reason why Kobe Bryant is compared to and then not compared to Michael Jordan. The reason is the same reason why Phil Jackson is the best coach ever and then needs to be fired (in the eyes of some Lakers fans)? Most fans, media, and the world are extremely short-sighted. It can be termed the bandwagon syndrome. The &lsquo;What Have You Done For Me Lately&rsquo; disease. When people form their opinions, they very often fail to grasp all the knowledge available to make that decision. They simply form their opinion based on the latest thing that they read, saw, or heard. That was the case here. The Celtics had been taken to 7 games by the below .500 Hawks and the average Cavaliers. The Lakers had somewhat coasted to the Finals by defeating the talented Utah Jazz and the defending champ Spurs, therefore, they should be favored right? All the experts thought so. But the so-called experts failed to see the big picture. The Celtics were the NBA&rsquo;s best team all season. They won 66 games. They had the NBA’s largest point differential, which ESPN’s John Hollinger has shown to be the best indicator of playoff success in the past. They are, in my opinion, the NBA&rsquo;s best team since the 2002 Lakers. They were by far the NBA’s best defense throughout the season and simply put, defense wins championships. I hold firmly by my previous statement that a great offense always beats a great defense. The one problem is that a great offense is much more difficult to execute on a consistent basis than a great defense. Offense is more skill than defense. Defense is more effort than offense. When a great defensive team struggles offensively, they are able to sustain great effort on the defensive end in order to stay in a game. The opposite is not true for a great offensive team. It was nice to hear in the post-game news conference from Kobe Bryant that the Lakers need to focus more on the defensive end to win a championship. Their 2009 title run starts right there.</p>
<p>Another symptom of the bandwagon syndrome is the immediate need to call for wholesale changes. There are numerous threads already on the Lakers forums calling for trades acquiring other players (Artest, Redd, Iguodala, Brand) while shipping out some of the disappointments and inconsistencies from the Finals (Odom, Gasol, Radmanovic, Walton). Major changes to the Lakers roster are not necessary. They could use some minor tweaks, but the fact is that the Lakers have the #1 pick in the 2008 draft and they have selected Andrew Bynum. Bynum would be a junior coming out of college this season and he would undoubtedly be the first pick. Bynum will bring what most critics claim the Lakers lacked in this years’ playoffs: defense, toughness, and rebounding. It remains to be seen if a trio of Bynum, Odom, and Gasol can co-exist; the lack of enough three-point shooters around them could be an issue. Additionally, the Lakers are one of the NBA’s youngest teams. They will certainly improve. If each player improves even close to as much as they did last offseason, a championship is likely.</p>
<p>To give a quick overview of Game 6, I still love Rajon Rondo as a player. As I said earlier, he has the potential to become an NBA All-Star if he can develop a jumper. He destroyed the Lakers on both sides of the floor with his quickness and effort all over the floor. I actually thought the Lakers defense was better in this game. They made the adjustment to switch the pick-n-roll and it worked well. The problem was that the Celtics had their best shooting game and best complete defensive effort of the series. If that pick-n-roll adjustment had been made earlier in the series, the series could have turned out differently. Pau Gasol’s softness hurt the Lakers as well. He is simply not a true center; he must be dreaming about playing alongside Bynum more than anyone. Bynum will allow Gasol to play against physically weaker guys. I do not think I have ever seen Gasol sky up and grab a rebound. It always seems as if he barely gets a fingertip on it before he grabs it. His four early turnovers also hurt. But, I still believe he is an amazing fit for the triangle offense and now that his flaws have been exposed on a grand stage, he has an immense amount of room to still improve. He also has the hardest working man in the game pushing him to strive to get better. I have further things to say about Kobe and his performance this season but I am saving that material for a future article. One other thing you have to remember is that this Lakers team has only been together for a few months. The Celtics team was established before training camp and they have had far more time to mesh as a team. Lastly, the season was far from a disappointment. When the Lakers first acquired Pau Gasol, fans were arguing about whether or not the Lakers could win the title once Andrew Bynum returned. Well, Bynum never returned and the Lakers still came within two games of a championship.</p>
<p>120 days until 2008-2009 NBA Training Camp, let’s go!</p>
<p>Before that occurs, it is time for American Basketball to move onto the Olympics. The squad went undefeated last year at FIBA Americas and they hope to continue that streak onto the USA’s first gold medal since 2000. I will give a preview of the team after the final 12 man squad is announced Monday. I will say one thing though, they will win Gold. The team is not only stacked but they have a new-found commitment to defense and defense wins gold medals too.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Game 5 Thoughts</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/game-5-thoughts/</link>
			<pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/game-5-thoughts/</guid>
			<description>Thoughts on the Lakers&#39; 103-98 victory in Game 5 of the 2008 NBA Finals.
  Very interesting game, eerily similar to Game 4 but the Lakers were able to show fight and held on in the end. The resiliency of the Celtics is very impressive. They do not give up. The attitude stems from the personalities of their two leaders, Paul Pierce and Kevin Garnett. The two are fearless, passionate leaders who are on the verge of their first NBA title.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thoughts on the Lakers' 103-98 victory in Game 5 of the 2008 NBA Finals.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Very interesting game, eerily similar to Game 4 but the Lakers were able to show fight and held on in the end. The resiliency of the Celtics is very impressive. They do not give up. The attitude stems from the personalities of their two leaders, Paul Pierce and Kevin Garnett. The two are fearless, passionate leaders who are on the verge of their first NBA title.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Mike Breen, Jeff Van Gundy, and Marc Jackson are by far my favorite broadcasting team in the NBA. Kevin Harlan is a great play-by-play guy, but as a team, you cannot beat this trio. JVG is a former NBA head coach who emphasized defense above all else. He critcized the Lakers defense harshly and repeatedly during the Game 5 broadcast and he was 100% correct.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Lakers had no answer for Paul Pierce. No one on the Lakers can even stay in front of him except Kobe. If the Lakers had a guy like Raja Bell, Bruce Bowen, James Posey, or even Tony Allen, they would be having a far easier time in this series. Pau Gasol&rsquo;s inability to hedge the pick-and-roll effectively is also a reason for the defensive shortcomings.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Jordan Farmar came up HUGE in Game 5. Sam Cassell and Eddie House do not have the lateral foot speed to stay in front of him. Phil Jackson realized this and gave Farmar some opportunites to take it to the rim. Additionally, Farmar is very effective at finishing up at the rim around the bigs.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Lamar Odom and Pau Gasol both had their best games of the series and are going to need to produce at a similar clip in order to force a Game 7. One big gripe is their continued inability to secure tough rebounds. The Celtics have stolen too many offensive and defensive rebounds after Odom or Gasol have been the first to get a hand on it. Rajon Rondo did this multiple times. I really like Rondo as a player. He is quick, tough, can pass, takes care of the ball, defends extremely well, and plays very hard. If he can develop an outside shot, he could become an All-star in this league. Only 22 years old.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Anyone who thinks the Kobe steal in the final minute was a foul has not been watching the same series as I have. That foul might be called in middle school basketball, but in these NBA Finals, no chance. If that was a foul, then James Posey and PJ Brown would foul out in their first 2 minutes of play. This series has been extremely physical and that was definitely not a foul. On another note, the Sam Cassell And-1 against Jordan Farmar was a horrible call. But to balance it out, KG&rsquo;s 5th foul on Gasol was another blown call. Those kinds of calls &ldquo;usually&rdquo; even out. There are exceptions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Paul Pierce played over 47 minutes. Hopefully for the Lakers he shows some effects of this in Game 6 after only one day of rest, but I think he will be perfectly fine.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>ESPN continues to be relentlessly biased against Kobe Bryant. It is ridiculous. Jon Barry blasted Kobe after the Game 5 victory saying he could not believe that Kobe deferred the ball to Pau Gasol down the stretch and how Michael Jordan would never do that, blah, blah, blah. I, as a Lakers fan, was absolutely ecstatic that Kobe did so. He realized that Pau was scoring well against KG and that it was probably the best chance for the Lakers to score. Kobe realized that every time he drove, there were 4 Celtics on him and that instead of him launching a long jump shot over a contested hand, it would be better for the Lakers to post Gasol. Gasol scored quite a few buckets over KG in the final quarter. How can you possibly criticize Kobe for this effective strategy that led to a WIN. I do not know. But, ESPN finds a way to do that.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I also love how the ESPN analysts rip Phil Jackson for moves he makes after the results of the moves are known. If the move turns out bad (such as the inserting of Chris Mihm), the analysts rip into Phil exclaiming how stupid the move was. Wow, how insightful of you guys. The fact is that Ronny Turiaf was having an atrocious series and Phil wanted to try Mihm. Jon Barry (never coached an NBA game in his life) blasts Phil at half-time confused at how a Hall-of-Fame coach could make such a stupid move. Shut-up Jon Barry.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>One thing that the analysts were correct about is that it is gonna take a much better effort and game to win in Boston. The Celtics did not play particularly well save for Pierce and their team defense. On the other hand, the Lakers did not play particularly well save for Farmar, Odom, and Gasol. Both their offense and defense could improve. The analysts are seeing the performance as a negative and that the Celtics should win easily in Game 6, but perhaps this is a positive for the Lakers as they have more to improve before Game 6. If they can create enough of an improvement, the series will go 7.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The only thing that is missing from this series being considered as one of the best Lakers-Celtics series of All-Time is the 7th game, so let&rsquo;s have one.</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Series Thoughts through Game 4</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/series-thoughts-game-4/</link>
			<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/series-thoughts-game-4/</guid>
			<description>I have been gone for the last week with no access to a computer or the internet but I managed to watch Games 2-4 of the NBA Finals. Here are some of my thoughts.
  The free throw disparity of 38-10 in Game 2 was a little much. You could argue the Celtics were more aggressive which they were and it is also apparent in the NBA that home-court advatange consistently benefits the home team in regards to fouls and referee calls, but a 28 free throw disparity in a 6 point game is unfortunate.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been gone for the last week with no access to a computer or the internet but I managed to watch Games 2-4 of the NBA Finals. Here are some of my thoughts.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The free throw disparity of 38-10 in Game 2 was a little much. You could argue the Celtics were more aggressive which they were and it is also apparent in the NBA that home-court advatange consistently benefits the home team in regards to fouls and referee calls, but a 28 free throw disparity in a 6 point game is unfortunate.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Back to Game 2, great comeback by the Lakers, but again too little, too late. Paul Pierce had a sensational game. When Pierce and Allen are making practically every 3-pointer that they take, the Celtics are unbeatable. Similarly, if the Lakers are hitting every 3-pointer that they take, they can come back from a 20 point deficit as they did in this game. As much as the Celtics' defense has dominated the Lakers at times during the series, Great Offense will always defeat Great Defense.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The small lineup (benching Lamar) was very effective during the comeback and Phil Jackson may have to employ it early and often tonight if the Lakers are to extend the series.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Game 3 was simply a sloppy game that the Lakers pulled out at home. Nothing much more to say about that. Kobe had his best game of the series and Sasha Vujacic, the best of his career. Those 2 were all the Lakers needed to win the game. Unfortunately this is not true for the series. Ray Allen continues to stroke which makes Laker fans wish we would have been fortunate enough (as Detroit was) to have his shooting slump during our series.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Now on to Game 4. I almost cannot even write about this. I have never been so emotionally vested in any team in my life as I have been with this Laker team. I watched that game at a Pizza Parlor in the small town of Sangar, CA with numerous intoxicated Northern Californians rooting for the Lakers' demise. Not to mention it was my 22nd birthday. Just a horrible game, a horrible day, and my worst birthday ever.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Enough of the national media has blasted the Lakers, their coach, and their MVP that I really do not need to go into it. I do not feel like defending them because the next great thing that they do will be praised only to be followed shortly thereafter by another bashing. The media in this country is ridiculous and that is really all that can be said. I may write more on this topic after the Finals.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Final thought. I believe this series will go 7 games. I may be saying this as a Laker fan as I told you earlier, it is impossible for me to be completely unbiased when talking the Lakers. Every subsequent game is the toughest of the year for the Lakers. They can definitely win Game 5 in L.A., come out strong and steal Game 6 and send it to 7. If they somehow do that, Game 7 will be darn near impossible to win after the emotion and energy they would have expended to reach it, but Game 7 is Game 7 and you never know what can happen. The Lakers ultimate goal right now is not to win the series, but to reach Game 7. Let&rsquo;s see if they can do it.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="http://archive.boston.com/sports/basketball/celtics/articles/2008/06/15/with_burden_on_kobe_should_he_have_a_beef/?page=full">Good Article regarding the media&rsquo;s unfair treatment of Kobe</a> by Bob Ryan of the Boston Globe, one of the best sports writers in America.</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Game 1 Thoughts</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/game-1-thoughts/</link>
			<pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/game-1-thoughts/</guid>
			<description>The Los Angeles Lakers and Boston Celtics squared off in Game 1 of their highly touted NBA Finals Series last night in Boston. The Celtics prevailed 98-88. Here are some of my thoughts on the game.
  First and foremost, the Celtics won the game. There were some questionable calls and a lot of in-n-outs, but those can always be excuses; the Celtics played well and won the game.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Los Angeles Lakers and Boston Celtics squared off in Game 1 of their highly touted NBA Finals Series last night in Boston. The Celtics prevailed 98-88. Here are some of my thoughts on the game.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>First and foremost, the Celtics won the game. There were some questionable calls and a lot of in-n-outs, but those can always be excuses; the Celtics played well and won the game.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The biggest reason the Celtics won is with what has been plaguing the Lakers since Andrew Bynum went down with a season-ending injury. Rebounding and interior toughness. The Celtics won the rebounding battle (46-33). Pau Gasol had 0 rebounds in the 1st half and only 3 points in the 2nd half. Pau needs to be more assertive on offense and needs to find a man and box him out on every defensive possession. Kevin Garnett and Leon Powe grabbed several key offensive rebounds with Gasol merely standing and watching.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Some of this blame also has to goto Lamar Odom. Throughout his career, he has been one of the most talented players in the league. A 6-10 Power Forward with guard-like handles. The problem with LO is that he is also one of the most inconsistent players in the league. He has improved this season especially after the acquisition of Gasol, but he needs to take it to another level if the Lakers want to win this series. Six rebounds in 40+ minutes is unacceptable.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It should also be noted that neither Lamar or Gasol are centers, they are both quick, versatile power forwards. Off the bench comes Ronny Turiaf, a more raw, tougher power forward. Still, the lack of a true center is what has hurt the Lakers. On another note, if you could combine the skill level of Gasol with the defense, toughness, and aggressiveness of Turiaf, you would find a player in the same league as a Tim Duncan. Bold statement, I know, but think about it.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The dramatics of Paul Pierce are another reason the Celtics were able to gain momentum and pull out the victory. I mean, come on, carried off the court and then in a wheelchair only to return a few minutes later running the fast break and banging 3&rsquo;s with no noticeable limp. A bit of a drama queen if you ask me. But it was a knee injury and basketball players do freak out when they feel something weird happen in their knees. Pierce coming out to the &lsquo;Rocky&rsquo; theme was a nice touch by the Celtics sound crew.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Sam Cassell is one of the more selfish players in the NBA. I, as a Laker fan, was glad to see him jack up early shots and make them. The cockiness from those shots led him to take several bad ones down the stretch. He never ran the offense when he was in; he dribbled around a few screens looking for an inch of space to jack up a shot.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Phil Jackson is going to have to play Trevor Ariza in this series, because Paul Pierce torched Vladimir Radmanovic.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The key to the Celtics win was their great 4th quarter defense. They held the Lakers to 15 points. Kobe took way too many jump shots as he tends to do at times. I do not know if this was due to the Celtics defense or Kobe&rsquo;s unwillingness to drive into the lane, but Kobe needs to change his game plan.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Kobe&rsquo;s defense needs to improve. He is a great help defender, but his tendency to over-help hurts the team as shown on two key Paul Pierce 3&rsquo;s in the 3rd quarter.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ray Allen played well, but Sasha Vujacic did a solid job on him save for a couple dumb fouls. Sasha&rsquo;s defense will improve as the series goes on, but that is a key matchup to watch as Sasha is pretty much their 6th starter in these playoffs.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>My biggest gripe about the game is that stupid HUGE NBA Championship trophy at mid-court. What the heck is the point of a half-court stripe if you cannot see it. There were two key plays called against the Lakers that were possibly muffed because of the lack of visibility of the half-court line. I have a feeling this will be changed next season.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Lastly, Laker fans should be concerned but not worried. This is the fifth Game 1 that Phil Jackson has lost during his run as a head coach. 3 of the first 4 still led to NBA Titles. Phil is arguable the best coach in the NBA at making mid-game and series adjustments. The Celtics showed that they have what it takes to win the NBA Title, now it is up to the Lakers to show the same in a pivotal Game 2 matchup Sunday in Boston.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I will be on vacation for the next week, so my next update will not be until after Game 4 in L.A.</p>
<p>Please disagree with me and leave comments or perhaps even agree. Thanks for reading.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>My Teams</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/my-teams/</link>
			<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/my-teams/</guid>
			<description>The name of my blog is a tribute to the late great Chick Hearn. His most famous phrase came when the Lakers had all but clinched a victory in the late moments of a game and Chick would put the game &amp;lsquo;in the refrigerator.&amp;rsquo; I grew up listening to and learning from Chick and I will always remember him.
This is a blog about sports and I will try my hardest to keep it focused strictly on that subject.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The name of my blog is a tribute to the late great Chick Hearn. His most famous phrase came when the Lakers had all but clinched a victory in the late moments of a game and Chick would put the game &lsquo;in the refrigerator.&rsquo; I grew up listening to and learning from Chick and I will always remember him.</p>
<p>This is a blog about sports and I will try my hardest to keep it focused strictly on that subject. When I say sports, I really do not mean sports. I mean the sports I watch and follow. Basketball is going to be the subject of most of the posts, but the blog might also include some baseball and football. I can uncomfortably call myself an expert on the game of basketball and most things surrounding it. With baseball and football, I have played them before but my knowledge is not nearly as extensive as basketball. Therefore, my takes about the two will be a little bit more elementary than my takes about basketball. I hope that is ok.</p>
<p>I will try to be un-biased in my posts as much as I can but you need to understand that I grew up in Southern California. So any takes about the Lakers or Dodgers are going to be subconsciously biased. But I will try, and like I said earlier some of my takes may surprise you. I am not the typical Laker fan. But I am a HUGE Laker fan. My parents always tell me a story about them watching the 1986 NBA Playoffs when my mom was pregnant with me. That year the Lakers were devastatingly upset by the Houston Rockets who went on to get rocked by the Boston Celtics in the Finals. As you can see, I have been a Laker fan since before I was born. Growing up, my father only really followed basketball therefore I did not become a Dodger fan until I was around 10. And since there was no NFL team in L.A., I took a liking to Peyton Manning and the Indianapolis Colts. I became a fan after the Colts’ drafting of Peyton Manning (who I loved at Tennessee) and Edgerrin James (who demolished UCLA and their National Title hopes in 1998). My friends like to roast me claiming I became a fan only after they became good, but that is not true. I will say that I am actually a Peyton Manning fan more than a Colts fan. In contrast, I am a Lakers fan more than I am a Kobe fan. No matter if Kobe stays or leaves, I will live and die with the Lakers. I also follow college hoops a great deal so you can expect some of that.</p>
<p>Anyways, enough with the small talk, let’s get this blog started.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Why A Blog?</title>
			<link>nitinsavant.com/posts/why-a-blog/</link>
			<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/why-a-blog/</guid>
			<description>After 22 great years of my life, I have decided to start a blog. I guess you could call me sort of an internet junkie. I spend hours upon hours every day cruising the web reading countless articles, blogs, product reviews, and anything else that catches my eye. I really could not imagine my life without a computer or the internet. What would I do? Anyways, a large majority of those hours spent perusing the internet is dedicated to sports.</description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After 22 great years of my life, I have decided to start a blog. I guess you could call me sort of an internet junkie. I spend hours upon hours every day cruising the web reading countless articles, blogs, product reviews, and anything else that catches my eye. I really could not imagine my life without a computer or the internet. What would I do? Anyways, a large majority of those hours spent perusing the internet is dedicated to sports. I am a HUGE sports fan. I have been my entire life. I grew up in Sunny Southern California playing the typical sports that every young kid plays including Baseball, Basketball, and Soccer. I went on to play basketball in high school and also in college at a small Division III school. Basketball is my true passion. I love each and every aspect of the game. And that is exactly what it is. Just a game. I know non-sports fans who believe that spending so much time on a game is a complete waste. I am not talking about the exercise part either. The watching, the reading, the arguing, and the agonizing over sports and your favorite sports teams. I really cannot explain it, but I guess it is kind of an addiction. I wish I worked as hard in school as I do intently watching and re-watching Laker games or reading up on the latest Laker trade rumors. But I don&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>So I decided to start a blog because anyone who knows me would say that I am a very opinionated person when it comes to Sports. My takes (to steal a phrase from Jim Rome) are not always what you would expect from me but I try to keep them honest and well-thought out. What better place to &lsquo;think out&rsquo; my sports takes than in a blog. In high school I hated writing essays and papers. Since then I have developed an appreciation for great writing and more importantly the content that comes with the great writing. I am by no means a great writer, but I think I could pass for a decent writer and hopefully my writing isn&rsquo;t so bad that you might actually read my stuff. Another thing, I didn&rsquo;t start this blog for people to read it. I started it for myself, but obviously it would be great if people actually read and enjoyed my writing.</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
