<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nitin Savant</title>
    <link>nitinsavant.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Nitin Savant</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="nitinsavant.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What is this Snapchat thing?</title>
      <link>nitinsavant.com/posts/snapchat/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/snapchat/</guid>
      <description>While in Istanbul, I met a bright Turkish teenager while eating at the dorm cafeteria. We chatted for a bit and as I got up to leave, I asked if he had Facebook. He said, &amp;ldquo;no, but I have Snapchat.&amp;rdquo;
I first tried Snapchat in late 2012, about a year after it&amp;rsquo;s launch. The app let you to take and share photos with your friends. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t really get it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Over It</title>
      <link>nitinsavant.com/posts/get-over-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/get-over-it/</guid>
      <description>I did it. After 3 years of using my iPhone 5 — one of the sleek 4-inch phones they don&amp;rsquo;t make anymore — without a case, it finally happened. I cracked my screen. As I removed my gym towel from my backpack today, my iPhone fluttered out behind it and smacked onto my room&amp;rsquo;s tile floor.
It sucked. Not because I needed a new phone. It still works. Not because I had to squint through a spider web to use it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If You&#39;re Not Going To Listen...</title>
      <link>nitinsavant.com/posts/advice/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/advice/</guid>
      <description>After just a few hours walking through Istanbul, I feel a distinctly different vibe from the rest of Europe. Istanbul is what&amp;rsquo;s known as a transcontinental city — a city that spreads across multiple continents, Europe and Asia in this case. And it shows. The food is spicier, the clothing is more traditional, and there isn&amp;rsquo;t much English to be heard. Before catching my flight from Croatia to Istanbul, I made use of my last opportunity to eavesdrop and heard this tidbit from the dinner table next to me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simple Pleasures</title>
      <link>nitinsavant.com/posts/simple-pleasures/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/simple-pleasures/</guid>
      <description>I know. It&amp;rsquo;s been a month since I wrote, and that last one doesn&amp;rsquo;t even count. Since then, I spent 10 exhausting yet amazing days home in Los Angeles and then another week battling jet lag while getting settled in Croatia. We&amp;rsquo;re staying in Cavtat, a small coastal town at Croatia&amp;rsquo;s southern tip. The city is full of tourists, and you can&amp;rsquo;t really blame &amp;lsquo;em. With dozens of seafood restaurants, strikingly clear blue water, and daily sunsets that flood the sky with color; Cavtat is the perfect place to spend a summer vacation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Movies</title>
      <link>nitinsavant.com/posts/movies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/movies/</guid>
      <description>On a random night a few months ago, I asked my roommate how many movies he thought he&amp;rsquo;d watched in his life. Fast forward four hours, it&amp;rsquo;s 2AM, my roommate is fast asleep, and I finish the list. I like making lists; there&amp;rsquo;s something about making a list that&amp;rsquo;s fun. Before you click below, take a guess at how many movies you&amp;rsquo;ve watched in your life.
Movies</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;m Traveling</title>
      <link>nitinsavant.com/posts/why-im-traveling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/why-im-traveling/</guid>
      <description>One country down, eleven to go. I almost wrote about how the month flew by, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure that was true. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;ll dig deeper. Until now I haven&amp;rsquo;t said much about why I&amp;rsquo;m traveling.
Over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve read a lot of self-help material. Too much. I figured there was a universal formula for happiness, and I set out to find it. I stopped using social media and watching television.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cafe in the Dark</title>
      <link>nitinsavant.com/posts/cafe-in-the-dark/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/cafe-in-the-dark/</guid>
      <description>A group of us recently visited what&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;Cafe in the Dark.&amp;rdquo; It is what it sounds like, a place to hang and drink coffee in the dark. But it&amp;rsquo;s not just dark, it&amp;rsquo;s pitch-black. Upon arriving, a blind host led three friends and I inside to our table. We shuffled along in a single file line, placing our right hand on the right shoulder of the person in front, and praying that we didn&amp;rsquo;t fall flat on our faces.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Freshman Year</title>
      <link>nitinsavant.com/posts/freshman-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/freshman-year/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been in Prague for 10 days now, and it feels like freshman year of college. It&amp;rsquo;s been both amazing and overwhelming. Upon arriving, they divided us among six hotels across the city. With everyone so excited to meet and become best friends, there was lots of energy in the air. And with beers costing a little over $1, there was plenty of social lubricant as well.
It&amp;rsquo;s been amazing to hear each person&amp;rsquo;s story about they heard about Remote Year and how they then mustered the courage to do it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Packing List</title>
      <link>nitinsavant.com/posts/packing-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/packing-list/</guid>
      <description>For my year abroad, I&amp;rsquo;m attempting to travel light while staying prepared for different situations with regards to weather, laundry, pickpockets, etc. I did tons of research, but after just one day in Prague, I realized that it was mostly a waste. Months of googling was quickly trumped by one day of actual experience. On the bright side, with a duffel that&amp;rsquo;s literally the maximum size allowed for a carry-on, I was able to get by without checking any bags.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Remote Year</title>
      <link>nitinsavant.com/posts/remote-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>nitinsavant.com/posts/remote-year/</guid>
      <description>On June 1st, I&amp;rsquo;m leaving the country for a year. The plan is to spend one month in twelve different cities across the world. The trip includes 75 others and is organized by Remote Year. Here&amp;rsquo;s where we&amp;rsquo;ll be from June 2015 - May 2016:
 Prague, Czech Republic (Jun) Ljubljana, Slovenia (Jul) Cavtat, Croatia (Aug) Istanbul, Turkey (Sep) Penang, Malaysia (Oct) Ko Pha Ngan, Thailand (Nov) Hanoi, Vietnam (Dec) Kyoto, Japan (Jan) Buenos Aires, Argentina (Feb) Montevideo, Uruguay (Mar) Santiago, Chile (Apr) Lima, Peru (May)  When I describe my trip to friends, many respond initially out of fear, while others are able to respond with joy.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
